<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Janus Alexandrus Ferrarius, an Augustine friar, his epistles to the two brethern of Wallenburgh, concerning the usefulness and necessity of the Roman Catholick faith wherein the ambition and avarice of the Church of Rome are lively demonstrated in a mathematical method, by a continued series of connexed propositions / from the original Latine.</title>
            <author>Fabricius, Johann Ludwig, 1632-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F73</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32018</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12295015</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12295015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58998</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41160)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58998)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1503:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Janus Alexandrus Ferrarius, an Augustine friar, his epistles to the two brethern of Wallenburgh, concerning the usefulness and necessity of the Roman Catholick faith wherein the ambition and avarice of the Church of Rome are lively demonstrated in a mathematical method, by a continued series of connexed propositions / from the original Latine.</title>
                  <author>Fabricius, Johann Ludwig, 1632-1697.</author>
                  <author>Fabricius, Joannes Ludovicus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 142 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Ratcliffe and Nathaniel Thompson, and are to be sold at their house ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of Latin original attributed by Wing to Joannes Ludovicus Fabricius.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58998:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58998:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Janus Alexandrus Ferrarius,</hi> An Auguſtine FRIAR, HIS EPISTLES To the TWO BRETHREN OF <hi>WALLENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Concerning the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SEF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LNESS</hi> and <hi>NECESSITY</hi> OF THE ROMAN CATHOLICK FAITH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein the</hi> Ambition <hi>and</hi> Avarice <hi>of the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> ROME <hi>are Lively Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a</hi> Mathematical Method, <hi>by a Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued</hi> Series <hi>of</hi> Connexed <hi>PROPOSITIONS.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>— Ridenti dicere verum</l>
               <l>Quis vetat?</l>
            </q>
            <p>From the Original Latine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Ratcliffe,</hi> and <hi>Nathaniel Thompſon,</hi> and are to be Sold at their Houſe in <hi>Newſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Shoe-Lane.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58998:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58998:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable ANTHONY EARL of <hi>SHAFTSB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY, &amp;c.</hi> Lord HIGH CHANCELLOR OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thoſe <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Weighty</hi> Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to which your Great <hi>Worth</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities,</hi> approved by the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the moſt <hi>Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced</hi> King of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> have <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58998:3"/>you, can <hi>Admit</hi> of any <hi>Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement,</hi> it will not, <hi>I hope,</hi> be thought a <hi>Sin</hi> in me, if I have Attempted thus to Contribute ſomething towards it, or if it ſhould, yet be pardoned as the Fault of a <hi>too haſty</hi> Zeal, in a Perſon <hi>deſirous</hi> to <hi>thruſt</hi> himſelf amongſt the <hi>croud</hi> of your <hi>Adorers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>deſervedly</hi> have you, <hi>my Lord, Drawn</hi> the Hearts and Affections of the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation to <hi>your Self;</hi> and never did <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> ſo Unanimouſly <hi>agree</hi> in the Choice of ſuch a great Miniſter of State: Your <hi>Virtues</hi> making all the World <hi>Admire</hi> the Kings <hi>Judgment,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58998:3"/>and the Kings <hi>Judgment confirming</hi> to all the World, their long before <hi>entertained</hi> Opinion of your <hi>Virtues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King is, <hi>my Lord,</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all <hi>Popiſh</hi> pretences) ſole <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car</hi> and <hi>Vicegerant</hi> under God, in his own <hi>Realms</hi> and <hi>Dominions;</hi> and he has Choſen you his <hi>Subſtitute</hi> in the <hi>Management</hi> of his <hi>Highest</hi> and <hi>Greateſt</hi> Affairs, wherein your <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct</hi> has been ſuch, as has given him every day new <hi>Encouragement</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Work of his own Hands, and he cannot but with <hi>Delight</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> hear with what <hi>Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations</hi> of <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Content,</hi> the whole <hi>Body</hi> of the Nation <hi>Applaud</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58998:4"/>your <hi>Juſtice, Prudence,</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> whereby you have almoſt quite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved all <hi>Miſapprehenſions</hi> they had ſometime conceived againſt <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor has your Zeal in the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting</hi> and <hi>Defending</hi> the <hi>Settled</hi> and <hi>Eſtabliſhed</hi> Proteſtant Religion in this Kingdom, appeared leſs then your great <hi>Abilities</hi> in State, you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving largely Contributed your Counſel and Aſſiſtance both to <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the <hi>Weakning</hi> the hands of our <hi>common</hi> Enemy, and may therefore <hi>claim</hi> a Right to <hi>Divertiſe</hi> your Self at their <hi>Follies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But however, my Lord, this
<pb facs="tcp:58998:4"/>ſmall <hi>Preſent</hi> of mine prove, let not my <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Devotion</hi> be accounted a <hi>Crime,</hi> nor that be Blemiſhed as a <hi>Preſumption,</hi> which is a ſincere tender of my part of that Service and Affection which all men pay you, and which ſhall ever be Paid you by</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Faithful, moſt Humble, and moſt Obedient Servant, J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58998:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58998:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat</hi> Ignoble <hi>pair of</hi> Wallenburgh <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (to whom the following Epiſtles are written) Treacherous</hi> Hollanders, <hi>and</hi> Popiſh <hi>Renegado's, Created indeed, Titular Biſhops (the
<pb facs="tcp:58998:6"/>one of</hi> Adrianople, <hi>the other of</hi> My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia) <hi>but in troth,</hi> corrupt <hi>Pentioners of the</hi> Popes, <hi>and</hi> ſworn <hi>Slaves to that Servant of Servants, have for a long time</hi> exerciſed <hi>their</hi> mercinary <hi>Pens, and with</hi> united <hi>Forces, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently Employed all their</hi> Skill <hi>and</hi> Power, <hi>to ſettle and at length</hi> Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh <hi>that</hi> Synagogue <hi>of</hi> Satan, <hi>which has ſo long ſtood</hi> Tottering. <hi>And when all the old</hi> Deceits <hi>and</hi> Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>were</hi> Detected <hi>and</hi> Exploded, <hi>advanced new Methods and Ways, Hammered out of their own</hi> Brains; <hi>and among others, that</hi> Form <hi>in uſe among forreign</hi> Civilians, <hi>of</hi> Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Witneſſes, <hi>not</hi> ancient <hi>and</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58998:6"/>pure <hi>ones, but</hi> Corrupt <hi>ones of the Church of</hi> Rome; <hi>as if the</hi> Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony <hi>of that</hi> Queen and Mother of Harlots, <hi>were abundantly ſufficient to</hi> confirm <hi>all her</hi> Ridiculous, <hi>and for the most part</hi> Impious <hi>Tenents, whilſt ſhe Exhibited all things under the</hi> Regal <hi>Signature of</hi> Teſte meipſa; <hi>a Priviledge which even</hi> Chriſt <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the</hi> reverenced <hi>Head of the</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick <hi>Church truly called ſo, when</hi> converſant <hi>on Earth, ſcarce ever</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, <hi>or thought worth the</hi> Claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Epiſtles are</hi> Scourges <hi>to thoſe Brethren in</hi> Iniquity; <hi>nor (as the title of the Book ſeems to declare)
<pb facs="tcp:58998:7"/>are they ſo much Demonſtrations as Deriſions of the</hi> Roman <hi>Catholick Faith, under a vail of</hi> Kindneſs, <hi>and</hi> pretence <hi>of</hi> Reverence, <hi>ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, as we ſay, under the</hi> fifth <hi>Rib; For throughout the whole courſe of the Epiſtle, the</hi> Irony <hi>is pleaſantly play'd with:</hi> Sharp <hi>Taunts,</hi> witty <hi>Jests, and</hi> biting <hi>Reflections every where mixed, which the Author choſe rather to couch in the Latine Tongue, as most proper for treating of things concerning the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, and more applicable to the</hi> Wallenburgh <hi>Brethren, thoſe two new</hi> Atlas<hi>'s of the</hi> Papal <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58998:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But our Author both bears another name, and is by</hi> Nation <hi>an Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, (and why then ſhould ſo much Wit and Ingenility of their own be hid from the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>or only reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a few?) of no</hi> Ignoble <hi>Family, who enticed by the</hi> crafty <hi>Arts of thoſe</hi> Emiſſaries, <hi>was not only</hi> initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>in the Myſteries of the</hi> Papal <hi>Iniquities, but bred up in them, even to</hi> Surfeit <hi>and</hi> Lothing, <hi>till growing up to riper</hi> Judgment, <hi>they could no longer</hi> impoſe <hi>upon him thoſe</hi> por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentuous <hi>principles of</hi> Popery, <hi>which not only</hi> holy Writ, <hi>but</hi> ſober Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>utterly</hi> abhors; <hi>and which are even ſo</hi> repugnant <hi>to ſenſe, that they
<pb facs="tcp:58998:8"/>are rather to be</hi> hiſt <hi>at, and</hi> laſht <hi>by</hi> bitter <hi>Sarcaſms, then otherwiſe taken notice of, or endeavoured to be</hi> confuted <hi>by any thing of</hi> ſolid <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58998:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>JANUS ALEXANDRUS FERRARIUS OF THE</hi> AUGUSTIN ORDER. HIS Firſt Epiſtle Concerning the Uſefulneſs and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Faith. To the Right Reverend <hi>ADRIAN and PETER of WALENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any have valiantly, <hi>Moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Sirs,</hi> and with Various Succeſs, conteſted for the Welfare of the Church, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Hereticks, but ſcarce any with a caution, and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity like yours. For when Reaſon and Experience had taught us, that nothing hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath been more pernicious to our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58998:9"/>Republick,</hi> then that the moſt material and weighty Points contended for, ſhould be maintained by the authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp; ancient Principles of Chriſtianity; You from your admirable &amp; immenſe height of wit have made right diſcoveries, that things are not to be debated with <hi>poſitive</hi> Arguments or <hi>abſolutely pertinent</hi> to the matter, which the ſubtilty of Hereticks might eaſily either pervert or evade, but <hi>dilatory Exceptions</hi> are to be made uſe of, the <hi>Court of Scripture</hi> to be <hi>waved,</hi> and all Judges beſides the <hi>Pope</hi> to be <hi>refuſed;</hi> Or elſe what before all pleaſed you beſt, That title of long poſſeſſion and preſcription, was to be ſtretch'd upon the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and tedious cavils for worldly profit and advantage ſtarted: Which manner of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (of uſe indeed in Courts and Seats of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, but in matters relating to Faith and the underſtanding of Divine things utterly unheard of till now) when I more curiouſly conſidered, I could gather nothing elſe from it, but that you by an uncredible perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity of underſtanding had found out, that the Controverſies to be handled between Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks and Hereticks, were not to be treated in a Sacred and Religious, but Judicial and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58998:9"/>manner. For thus I revolved in my mind: <hi>Of what prevalency is preſcription againſt truth? Or, how does poſſeſſion juſtify error? Surely the underſtanding of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Brothers is more ſublime, their Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more exquiſite, their Judgments more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced, then to imagine that ſuch clamorous was of Judicial Reaſoning can ever be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to the ſearching out, or eſtabliſhing the truth of Divine Decrees. Whereupon I utterly began to believe they meant wholly another thing then what I firſt thought, and that they diſputed not for Religion, but Empire; not for Faith, but Obedience; and whilſt with ſo much anxious care, they endeavour to reduce Hereticks into the boſome of the Church, and labour to remove all cauſes of ſeparation; the main ſcope and aime of their contention is only, that they may at length ſubject them to the Empire of the Church, and diveſt them of their late gain'd liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I can ſcarce tell you <hi>Right Reverend Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> with how great, and how wonderful a light, this thought entred into my mind, and how clearly I immediately began to perceive what in this Argument (hitherto unaſſayed) was for the future with utmoſt care and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry to be garniſhed and imbelliſhed. To
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58998:10"/>wit, that in this your way of arguing, ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able matter was to be found out, Principles agreeing with their concluſions, and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Hypotheſes; fitted to every Theſis; That thoſe Doctrines of the Catholicks, which neither the Teſtimony of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nor the Principles of ancient Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty could not maintain, may now be not only defended by Judicial clamours, but demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by the profoundeſt Axioms of civil prudence; which if once allowed us, I eaſily fore-ſee the whole task performed. For who will hereafter doubt, but that to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing ſo vaſt and extenſive an Empire, ſtretching it ſelf over all Earthly Regions, and over moſt powerful Emperours, Kings, and Princes, though unwilling and ſtrugling againſt it, ſo that never was there any Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion extant like it, who I ſay will doubt, but that to lay ſuch a foundation, there was a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of more then humane prudence? Or who will hereafter believe it the ſole work of unarmed Eloquence, to make a weak, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warlike, inconſiderable man, the Succeſſor of a poor Fiſherman, boldly and unpuniſht, trample on the necks of fierceſt Emperours, &amp; with a nod alone drive Kings out of their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58998:10"/>Thrones; or, that he ſhould be believed to have a power over the Gates of Heaven, to ſhut and open them at his pleaſure, and with his breath confine as many Thouſand Souls, as he thinks fit, to the infernal Courts, and when he will, from thence releaſe them. In ſhort, that out of a fear of Extream and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal puniſhment, or the awe of ſome vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible earthly Divinity, not the Rude and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, but moſt civilized knowing Nations of the whole World, ſhould be perſwaded to adore him?</p>
            <p>There are three powers, to which Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, by a certain unavoidable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, ſeems ſubjected. AMBITION, AVARICE and LUXURY. Theſe no Philoſophical Precepts, nor civil Sanctions could ever reſtrain. One man alone is to be found, who with a Pride too lofty, and unſuitable to Humane Nature, tramples all theſe under his Fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and leads them in try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph after himſelf, binding the firſt by a <hi>Willing Obedience,</hi> the next by <hi>Poverty,</hi> and the laſt by <hi>Continency,</hi> in voluntary Chains, whilſt yet he, though the <hi>Servant of Servants,</hi> accounts Kings his Slaves and Vaſſals; whilſt deſtitute of <hi>Gold and Silver,</hi> has not only the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58998:11"/>whole Univerſe, but <hi>Pluto</hi>'s Region for his Patrimony, and though a Batchelor, and freed from the Marriage Yoke, makes uſe of what ſtranger Beds he pleaſes. Who-ever ſhall deliberately conſider theſe things, need not be tormented into a confeſſion, that who commits them; <hi>Lifts up himſelf above all that is called God, and over every Dignity, ſitting in the Temple of God as God, and boaſting himſelf as God!</hi> But thoſe things which are of God, Who will deny to be divine?</p>
            <p>He has certainly forſworn all reaſon, who ſhall imagine, that the deſtruction of all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is to be aſcribed to reaſon, or that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the dictates of common reaſon, that Captive reaſon is thruſt out and diſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, under the obedience of moſt prodigious faith.</p>
            <p>Shall we attribute that to humane ſenſe, which charmes, and bewitches all Senſe? when no torments, no terrors can affright us from teſtiſying thoſe things to be true, which both ſight, hearing, touching, ſmell, and taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and all that is of ſenſe in us does open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and conſtantly gain-ſay. Who then does not perceive that the perſwaſion of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58998:11"/>Catholick Faith, is derived from far diſtant Principles?</p>
            <p>The Hereticks indeed confeſs that the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Apoſtles was divine. Yet was it not ſo ſublime, that they could conceive by what art upon ſuch ſlender foundations, and in their Nature ſo unproper for ſuch Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as they ſaw laid by their great Maſter <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſo vaſt a weight of Empire ſhould be built; though Evangelical ſtory teſtifies them ſufficiently ambitious and deſirous of Reign, and conſequently not altogether incurious, after Political Myſteries. But if therefore that Divine wiſdom, which fell upon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, if when compared to this of ours be but meer folly, and inſufficient to raiſe the Fabrick of this our holy dominion, with what Elogies ought the wiſdom of our <hi>Popes</hi> to be celebrated? Certainly it may well be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Divineſt, that ſo far ſurpaſſes the Divine it ſelf. For that it is Diabolical, not Hereticks themſelves dare affirm. All men confeſſing our <hi>Pope</hi> to be a moſt potent Prince, who not only Rules over part of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly,</hi> and in that o're the Head of the World, but ſtretches or impoſes his Dominion, into almoſt all Regions of the Earth, being Maſter
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58998:12"/>of ſo many Forts and Garriſons, as there are Churches and Monaſteries diſperſed through the World; and having ſo many Souldiers ready at his beck, as there are Friers and Monks there fed and fatned up. But now the Hereticks out of thoſe things which to this very intent the Apoſtle writ in his Letters to the Clergy and People of <hi>Rome,</hi> have learn'd, that <hi>There is no power, but it is of God. The Powers that be are ordained of God, ſo that whoſoever reſiſteth the power reſiſteth the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God.</hi> Rom. 13.1. With what face then can they deny the power of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to ariſe from God, or be of Divine Ordination? Who ought therefore them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſubject to this Ordination: And to that end the ſame Apoſtle elegantly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the <hi>Pope</hi> to be arm'd not with one, but two Swords.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is there Evil in the City, and God hath not done it?</hi> which the Prophet of the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> robs of the queſtion, and make an affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Doctrine. Yet themſelves cry out, there never was any greater evil extant, than the Pontifical Power, ſo that then of neceſſity they muſt grant it to be of God, and what
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58998:12"/>is of God; Who can deny to be Divine? But by the ſame means we have demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Churches Original to be from God, by the ſame in my Opinion, may its preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation be aſcribed to God, by what a Maſs of ſtudied Snares and Devices, by what a Power and Multitude of Engines have the Lords of the Earth ſtudied in all Ages to pull in pieces, and overthrow this Sacred Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, but all in vain, and to no purpoſe, that the whole World might take notice that the moſt juſt Judge of all things preſides over this Monarchy, whoſe Oracles have foretold its power to laſt many Ages, and to that end how liberally has he promiſed to enlarge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Mankind, the <hi>Spirit of Error and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Seducing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whither am I wandring? 'Tis not out of the Scriptures, as forreign; and not at all pertinent to the preſent purpoſe, but out of the proper and genuine Principles of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Faith of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, as far as it is by Proteſtant Hereticks oppoſed, that it is to be demonſtrated; which, I hope will be the more commodiouſly diſpatched, if we diſtinctly contemplate the admirable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58998:13"/>frame of this Religious Empire, diligently deliberating all its Laws, and all thoſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions repudiated, or rejected by the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</p>
            <p>In the treating of this, I had propoſed for my Method to follow <hi>Euclide,</hi> and from a few Fundamentals, raiſe the whole ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of this Sacred Monarchy; but taught by Experience, I found the Materials ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, ſo divers, and ſo contrary to themſelves thrown into one mighty Pile of Rubbiſh, by the Architects; but all with ſuch won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and cunning Arts cloſed and cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together, that it was not poſſible to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them all at one view; for, though ſome did appear, ſome were hid and covered over by others, that it would be too difficult in the Order wherein they are joyned, to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them fingly.</p>
            <p>Three only Fundamentals, omitting all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I have therefore pitcht upon. <hi>One De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition; One Axiom, or Propoſition; And one Poſtulatum, or Requeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58998:13"/>
            <p>
               <label>THE DEFINITION.</label> The Church is a Spiritual, but viſible Rule or Empire, wherein Men follow the preſcribed Faith, under one ſpiritual or viſible Head, to wit, the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yield him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable Obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The AXIOM, or PROPOSITION.</label> Whatſoever contributes to the Defence and Increaſe of this Church, that, and that only ought to be adjudged True, Holy, and Pious.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The POSTULATUM, or REQUEST.</label> May this Church extend it ſelf, even to the ends of the Earth.</p>
            <p>Though theſe be indeed the firſt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which of themſelves do not furniſh out the whole matter for demonſtration, yet they ſuffice to include all the other Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which in due time we ſhall bring to ſuch light, that not the moſt obſtinate He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks ſhall be able to doubt of them. But
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58998:14"/>the Reaſons by which I was induced more eſpecially to write to you, concerning this matter, <hi>Right Reverend Brothers,</hi> do already from what I have ſaid, ſo abundantly appear, that it would be ſuperfluous farther to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain them; and if you in your judgments ſhall approve this Holy Deſign, what I have now only vailed in Epiſtolary brevity, I ſhall more diligently hereafter digeſt into better order, and enlarge with comments, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring as much as in me lies, with all plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ingenuity to explain all the arts of the Catholick Religion.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>So Farewell in the Lord.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Cal. Aug.</hi> From the Birth of the Bleſſed Virgin, MDCLxvi.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="letter">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58998:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>JANUS ALEXANDRUS FERRARI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S OF THE</hi> AUGUSTIN ORDER. HIS Second Epiſtle Concerning the Uſefulneſs and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Faith. To the Right Reverend <hi>ADRIAN and PETER of WALLENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHat I lately promiſed you, <hi>Moſt Reverend Sirs;</hi> to demonſtrate in order, the Uſefulneſs and Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of all the ſeveral Heads of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Faith, now under your favour and protection, I attempt. Pardon that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, which the interpoſition of other affairs, that diſtracted me, hath hitherto cauſed, which I promiſe again to redeem by a future
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58998:15"/>complyance, and diligence; and in the mean time, let what I now offer, receive your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Cenſure.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place therefore, ſince the very Rule of Doctrine does require thoſe things to be prefer'd before all others, which will either afford the ampleſt light, or give the beſt aſſurance of accord. We judg we ought to take our beginning from the WORD of GOD, for though that may afford the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks never ſo ready and commodious, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to maintain their errors, yet by the incredible, and almoſt divine dexterity of ours, it has been uſed to be ſo well wreſted and turned, that our moſt advantageous Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents ſeem as aptly built upon it, as their moſt pernicious Opinions; Wherefore not only Catholick Writers, and amongſt thoſe the moſt renowned <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> but even the Fathers of the moſt holy oecumenical Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil held at <hi>Trent,</hi> adjudged all Treaties of Religion, ſhould thence have their original, and the Legat Cardinal <hi>de Monte</hi> propoſed <hi>The Word of God</hi> to be the firſt matter of all ſuch arguings,
<note place="margin">Hiſt concil. Trid. Lib. 6. c. 11.</note> 
               <hi>per Iſtabilire con quali Armi ſi doveſſe pugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re contra gli Heretici, ed in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58998:15"/>baſe doveſſere fondare la lor credenza i Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lici,</hi> to uſe the moſt eminent <hi>Pallavicini</hi>'s own words, <hi>for the eſtabliſhing with what arms the Hereticks were to be combated, and on what Foundations the Catholicks were to ground their Faith,</hi> &amp; we ſhall effectually ſhow what a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt confidence the Doctors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith ever had of forming the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, as though they were of wax, to their own party and purpoſe: For, though at that time, <hi>Er. Vincentius Lunellus</hi> (following the example of <hi>Sylveſter Prierius, Eckius,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their Predeceſſors) was of opinion the <hi>Church</hi> was to have the firſt place in diſpute, as the main and more ſolid Pillar of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, to which both Holy Writ and Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Authority ſhould only bowe, yet that counſel, though not proceeding from an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil mind, but certainly very imprudent and dangerous, was rejected by the other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, becauſe the authority of the Church, as then eſteemed, was to be fixed and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and ought not to be expoſed to the leaſt ſtretch of controverſy, for fear ſome impious or unwary mind ſhould chance to fall into, or ſtart a doubt. Therefore neither have we placed this <hi>Divinity of the Roman
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58998:16"/>Church</hi> amongſt thoſe truths that are to be demonſtrated, but even in our former <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et it down, as the firſt and indubitable Principle; and ſuch, that whoever durſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or call in queſtion, was not to be chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with weak and ineffective words, but fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſtripes, and unleſs he ſoon and ſeriouſly repented; (As a violater and defiler of the Spouſe of Chriſt, a diſturber of the Holy State, and a Traytor both to the divine and <hi>half-divine</hi> Majeſty) have his <hi>blaſpheming</hi> tongue cut out, or he taken from the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the living, and burnt in expiatory flames, according to Chriſts own command. <hi>If any one abide not in me,</hi> (that is, in the Church, which together with the head conſtitutes the body) <hi>he is caſt forth as a branch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. XV. Verſe vi.</note> 
               <hi>and is withered,</hi> (that is, being thrown out of the Communion of the <hi>Church,</hi> he is by various torments ſo macerated, and dried up, that he becomes fitter for fuel) <hi>and men gather up thoſe branches, and caſt them into the fire, and they are burnt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor indeed is there any other way, ſince from a common School-preſcript. <hi>Contra ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantem
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58998:16"/>principia non eſt diſputandum. There's no diſputing againſt a denier of Principles;</hi> We have already found out that the authority of the Church ought to be reckoned among thoſe things which the Philoſophers call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>indemonſtrables,</hi> which though they cannot themſelves be proved, yet may ſerve to prove others.</p>
            <p>Nor ought it to trouble us, though Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks make ſuch a clamorous babbling, that <hi>Indemonſtrables may be three wayes called ſo;</hi> For there are ſome which for their falſity or obſcur'd perplexity and incertainty cannot be demonſtrated: Others may be called <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrables,</hi> though they have ſuch and ſo plain a light of Truth, that our heart if never ſo little intent upon them, conſtantly approves them, and nothing can be propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that ſeems then them more firm and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: Others again may be called ſo, not that they are utterly not to be demonſtrated, but which already have been demonſtrated; ſo that they want not the utmoſt probation, but are taken in the progreſs of reſoning as Principles already certain and evident. They therfore (<hi>i.e.</hi> the Hereticks) that the authority of our Church is in the firſt ſenſe Indemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58998:17"/>out of <hi>deriſion</hi> eaſily grant. But the ſecond and third they deny; nay from thence they conclude taking it from your own hint. <hi>(Judgment without evidence or proof of the matter is but raſhly given)</hi> That it is a raſhneſs to believe the authority of the Church; Yet am I of the mind that it is all thoſe three wayes; and therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſimply and perfectly indemonſtrable.</p>
            <p>For that it is ſo in the firſt ſignification, from hence manifeſtly appears, that by uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal confeſſion it pertains not to <hi>Knowledge,</hi> but to <hi>Faith,</hi> and therefore according to St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>an aſſent is required to Faith not made apparent;</hi> for as <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> truly ſayes. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>We embrace Faith from an indemonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Principle;</hi> for what he ſpeaks of the word of God, as it manifeſts it ſelf to him by its own light, we much more commodiouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce for the <hi>Church.</hi> Whence it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whilſt Faith by general conſent is ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, that 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Of things not ſeen,</hi> that likewiſe that propoſition. <hi>The Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is Miſtreſs of Divine Faith and manners,</hi> appears not of ſuch evident cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58998:17"/>There is therefore both for its falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and obſcurity, between this and other <hi>indemonſtrable</hi> Propoſitions, this vaſt and terrible difference, That the reſt onely <hi>cannot</hi> be demonſtrated, but this neither <hi>can</hi> nor <hi>ought.</hi> For certainly, That ought not to be done, which whilſt any one undertakes, he both makes himſelf a laughing-ſtock, and expoſes the whole matter to danger and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate. But whoſoever endeavours to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the Authority of the Roman Church out of its vulgarly known Principles, muſt as Experience witneſſes, of neceſſity run into many wild mazes and windings, or fall into greater obſcurities and uncertainties.</p>
            <p>Wherefore aſſenting herein with the very Hereticks themſelves, we conclude, That the Divinity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is in the firſt ſence <hi>indemonſtrable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how that may likewiſe be ſaid of the ſecond ſignification, will be of ſomewhat more difficult diſquiſition: for as you have very well hinted, <hi>Moſt Reverend Brothers, In vain do we ſeek for the evidence of things in the Roman Faith, as things which do not appear:</hi> that is, by the interpretation of the Apoſtle, <hi>things that have no being:</hi> from whence it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58998:18"/>happens, that when we hear thoſe words, <hi>The Roman Church is Miſtreſs of all,</hi> we do not immediately yield ſtedfaſt aſſent to it, as if it were an undoubted Truth, nor find we any force upon our Souls to conſtrain our belief of it. Wherefore this propoſition ſeems not to deſerve any place among thoſe which with one ſingle proſpect of the Mind are at once perceived and approved of by us. But yet indeed to remove that difficulty it ſhould diligently be weighed that the Mind of Man may be two ſeveral ways affected, for either it is ſimple and unbyaſſed by any thing of prejudice, or otherwiſe diſpoſed to ſome agreeing temper, and as it were ſeaſoned with ſome ſavour: for the moſt part it has not light proper for diſcerning this Truth, nay ſometimes is ſo abſolutely indocible to any belief, that without that light which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a flaming Faggot, it can never be effectually illuſtrated: but this is ſo ordained and eſtabliſhed without any arguing or fear of Error, that though as the Proverb ſays, <hi>The Church ſhould ſheep with both Eyes,</hi> yet it hath concluſively both for knowledge and all faith, that manly &amp; magiſterial <hi>Ipſa Dixit.</hi> But of ſuch a mind, the perception is like to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58998:18"/>that which when quickeſt ſighted deny the ſeeing of Phantaſms &amp; Viſions, it does pretend diſtinctly and accurately to ſee every thing, no otherwiſe then thoſe who beholding their firſt Vital Light on a Sunday, are reputed to ſee <hi>Fayries and Hobgoblins, and other Spirits of the Night, Wandring Fires, and Terrors of the Grave,</hi> which others in the cleareſt light, and under what Star ſoever born, nay though they had <hi>Lynceus</hi> his Eyes, cannot at all diſcern. Nor ought any one to derogate from this Judgment of ours, that in the manner we have declared many Spirits are ſo ſenſeleſs and inſipid as to adhere without any diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Examination to what has from their tendereſt age been taught them, or rather commanded them by their Nurſes and Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. For it does not from thence follow that in thoſe kinds of knowledge they ſhould not ſee as clear as others: for even Experience it ſelf teaches, That thoſe who are weak-ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed do in the thickeſt darkneſs ſee a thouſand ſtrange and diſcoloured Figures which fly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a quick and piercing Eye. Thus as thoſe who with the violence of a Feaver grow diſtracted, often fancy things in their imaginations which the ſoundeſt minds could
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58998:19"/>never conceive; yet neither weakneſs of Eyes, nor Feavers, nor Diſtractions are rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned among Vices: So though neither ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity nor folly, nor an unapt propenſion to Faith in any thing, are accounted among Virtues of the Mind, yet they are uſed ſo to inſtruct and perfect Man, as to make him at firſt view embrace this Principle of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Authority, and firmly adhere to it: for it is neceſſary that between our Faculties and thoſe Obſervations laid down to us, a certain due reaſon or proportion ſhould interpoſe, that as it is in the Proverb, <hi>Time and Straw ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens Medlars,</hi> that is, brings them to a perfect rottenneſs and corruption.</p>
            <p>None therefore need think it a wonder if what we have aſſerted concerning the <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Roman Church,</hi> do ſeem a little ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure to an Underſtanding not yet initiated or at all accuſtomed to our Principles, whilſt, that I may uſe the ſolemn words of our My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical <hi>Theology,</hi> he was ſo ſtupified that he was not capable of perceiving things not appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by reaſon of their being: for which he may confide in theſe Arts; and when he ſhall hereafter be modelled by our wiſemen, we
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58998:19"/>ſhall teach him in a larger and more peculiar manner.</p>
            <p>Thus have we manifeſted the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Doctrine of our Church in the firſt and ſecond Signification to be <hi>Indemonſtrable.</hi> There remains yet the third place that is how it may be termed ſo after a fram'd <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of demonſtration, which plainly appears in our firſt Epiſtle: for we have already there laid down the Demonſtration of the Popiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the power founded on it not to be framed or made out <hi>à Priori</hi> indeed as the Schoolmen have it; but nevertheleſs <hi>à Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore for trial-ſake onely, we will ſet down this one Argument, which after your Example we will give perfection to by this Triangular form:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That Power which no humane force can reſiſt, muſt needs deſcend from Heaven.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But no humane force could ever reſiſt the Power of the Church of ROME.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Therefore the Power of the Church of ROME is deſcended from Heaven.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Propoſition is clear in it ſelf, the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58998:20"/>next is proved by the Experience of many Ages: whereupon the third muſt needs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main firm and unſhaken. — <hi>Veluti Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſia Cautes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any be of ſo ſteady a Brain, that with whatever Syllogiſtical Circulation it be turn'd about and agitated, he can yet be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from giddineſs, he may likewiſe have <hi>by Witneſſes</hi> confirmed the Demonſtration of this Propoſition; after your Example, <hi>Moſt Reverend Men,</hi> who a year ago divulged that excellent way of proving things, ſo much wiſhed for by the Lawyers, and by which with ſo much ſucceſs you defended the Follies of I know not what <hi>Helmſtadt</hi> Divine; <hi>That hereafter you thought nothing ſolid was to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the Proteſtant Divines, if (to wit) they were ignorant of the Knowledge both of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Humane Laws.</hi> Such as heretofore in that <hi>Julian Academy</hi> were <hi>Calixtus, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringius,</hi> and their Scholars, a ſort of wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed lurking Knaves, and an untutored race of People.</p>
            <p>But though whole Regiments of Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes might be brought, who have writ of the Invincible Majeſty of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, I will now onely produce one; but ſuch an one
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58998:20"/>as both teſtifies of times paſt and to come, at once a Hiſtorian and a Prophet, the moſt bleſſed <hi>Campanella. For if,</hi> ſays he,
<note place="margin">De Monarc. <hi>Hiſp</hi> cap. xviii <hi>Quod ſi inquit,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>all Princes and People ſhould joyn their forces together to diſſolve the Papacy, yet they will never effect any thing: for if onely the Expedition of the</hi> Croiſſado <hi>were ſet on foot, all Religious Orders, of which there are ſo many Millions, would fly to Arms, and with their Tongues and Swords reſtore that, and ſtrike Terror into the Whole World; for neither would People dare to bear Arms againſt holy men; or if all did not, the greateſt part ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, the reſt affrighted would loſe their Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: for though the Pope ſhould be a wicked man, yet that Prince that ſhall dare to draw his Sword againſt him, will be overcome even whilſt a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour; a thing made manifeſt in</hi> Roger Guiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card <hi>King of</hi> Naples, <hi>who gaining the Battel, yet was compelled to kiſs the Popes Toe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay even the very ſame Syllogiſm (apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe things as we have ſaid with caution) may be proved by innumerable Teſtimonies out of Holy Writ, of which one may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: <hi>Rev.</hi> xiii. 7. <hi>And it was given</hi> (to wit, by God) <hi>to him</hi> (to the ſeven-hill'd Church)
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58998:21"/>
               <hi>to make war with the Saints and to overcome them, and power was given him over all Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, and Tongues, and Nations:</hi> whence ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed with an Admiration of her ſelf, ſhe cries out, <hi>I ſit as a Queen, and am no widow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow, Rev.</hi> xviii. 7. For it has a promiſe, that <hi>the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it,</hi> Mat. xvi. 18. And the reaſon of the promiſe, <hi>For if Satan be divided againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, how ſhall his Kingdom ſtand,</hi> Luke xi. 18.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As a late Philoſopher aſſumed an Authority of laying down his <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> as direct Certainties, on which might be laid a Superſtructure of the Univerſality of all things, and all <hi>Phaenonoma's</hi> thereby explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: ſo we to our Principle aſſume the ſame right, and confirm it by theſe two Syllogiſms:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That which ſo ſtrongly cements any vaſt Body compoſed of a thouſand parts, that no one part ſhakes or totters, is abſolutely a ſolid Foundation:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But by this Propoſition,</hi> That the Authority of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is Divine, <hi>the whole weight and body of the Papal Empire is cemented and knit together;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58998:21"/>
            <p>Again,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That in which all Doubts may be reſolved, and it ſelf not diſſolved, is the Firſt Principle of all Doubts:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But this Propoſition,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thus from You, <hi>Moſt Reverend Brothers,</hi> we have learn'd to <hi>Argue in Form,</hi> which is accounted to have ſuch a wonderful efficacy in perſwaſion, that I cannot doubt but the very Hereticks, ſtartled at theſe Syllogiſms, will be ready to give us their hands, which if they ſuddenly do not, we ſhall next proceed to Demonſtrations from the Word of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>In the mean time farewel.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Paris</hi> in the great <hi>Convent,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Cal, Octob.</hi> MDCLxvi.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="letter">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58998:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>JANUS ALEXANDRUS FERRARI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S OF THE</hi> AUGUSTIN ORDER HIS Third Epiſtle, Concerning the Uſefulneſs and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Faith, To the Right Reverend <hi>ADRIAN and PETER of WALLENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BY what Reaſon we have been induced to reckon <hi>the Authority of the Roman Church,</hi> amongſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Indemonſtrables;</hi> and why we determined to take the beginning of our Order of Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration from <hi>the Word of God,</hi> we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready at large Explained in the former Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. Wherefore we will now approach the main Point, firſt by Univerſal Theology,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58998:22"/>laying down ſimply and nakedly all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions controverted by the followers of <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> then ſingly if need be Explaining them; and in the laſt place bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them under Demonſtration, but as to what reſpects the Form and Manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them, though we had once deſigned to uſe Syllogiſtical Figures, we afterwards changed our mind, and more adviſedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to expreſs our Arguments in a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and more continued manner of Diſcourſe rather then to faſhion them after the Mode of <hi>Barbara,</hi> or impriſon them under the Modes of <hi>Celarent,</hi> and <hi>Felapton;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially whilſt all that Syllogiſtical Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (if we have regard to you) would in a manner be Vain and Uſeleſs, for I have heard that all things which you have uſurped ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with your Eyes or Ears, or but touched with the Tip of your Finger, are by a moſt wonderful Power (and yet not <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi>) ſtraight ways <hi>Triangulated</hi> into <hi>formal</hi> Syllogiſmes.</p>
            <p>THAT THEREFORE THE WHOLE MOST HOLY MONAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHY, MAY BE FORTUNATE AND HAPPY, and more ſafe and beneficial for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58998:23"/>the wafting all thoſe Invoke the <hi>Papal Deity</hi> into a more magnificent and ſplendid Life. Be thou the Firſt</p>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>PROPOSITION.</head>
               <p>That to the attaining Salvation, ſome Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is abſolutely neceſſary.</p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>EXPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>It may poſſibly be wondred at by ſome, that having propoſed the Demonſtration on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſuch Heads of the Catholick Faith, which the followers of <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Luther</hi> oppoſe; that we ſhould undertake the proof of this Propoſition, ſince they themſelves do not only defend it as a truth, but urge it as neceſſary, and judge all who think other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe worthy to be caſt out of Humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; but their wonder will ceaſe when they ſhall know that I have ſtated the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the ſame words indeed, but in a ſence quite different from the Hereticks, for as to the word RELIGION, that indeed ſounds the ſame to them and us. That is, <hi>The fear of ſome inviſible power Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted above humane Condition, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Def. </seg>1</label> which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58998:23"/>Mortals as more feeble, and inferiour to it, are to apply themſelves to, with all ſubmiſsive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence.</hi> But that word SAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VATION, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Def. </seg>2</label> though in the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> it be taken by both Parties in the ſame ſence, to wit, for <hi>the top and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of all Truth, Piety, and Holineſs, and therefore the end of all Religion:</hi> Yet <hi>ſpecially</hi> it uſurps a diverſe ſignification, for when in <hi>our only Axiom, Epiſt.</hi> 1. that only ought to be deemed Pious, True, and Holy, which tends to the Churches, that is <hi>(as in the ſame Epiſt.)</hi> to the Defence and Amplification of the Papal Empire; it will of neceſſity be gathered thence, that that word SALVATION ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to us, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Def. </seg>3</label> 
                     <hi>But a proſpect of the Vaſtneſs and Perpetuity of that Dominion, which under Chriſts Name, his Vicar Exerciſes here upon Earth.</hi> But the Hereticks in a quite different manner abuſe the word, to wit, by making it ſignifie I know not what imaginary Kingdom of Chriſt which they call Inviſible, here upon Earth <hi>Internal,</hi> but in the Heavens <hi>Eternal,</hi> and which with our Salvation (that is, <hi>with the Welfare and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of the Roman Empire</hi>) to have any
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58998:24"/>Conſiſtency, they expreſly deny. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in leaſt either ſide happen to Err, it is by the way to be obſerved: That by the Name of Roman Empire, no one is to underſtand that profane thing, which at preſent is Vulgarly called the <hi>German</hi> Empire, and by the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans <hi>Das Romiſche Reich,</hi> but that moſt truly Holy, yea Divine-Power, which our great <hi>Pope</hi> as <hi>Vice-god</hi> Exerciſes upon Earth; for as for the <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and other worldly Kings, they neither are in <hi>Rome,</hi> nor ſcarce get any Right in or from that City; nay, rather all they poſſeſs is ſolely from the Churches favour, holding it in Fee and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Title becoming her Vaſſals, whence it would be very Idle and Ridiculous to call them either Kings or Emperours of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</p>
                  <p>Therefore the Hereticks meaning of the word, differs from ours as far as <hi>Eaſt</hi> from <hi>Weſt,</hi> whilſt for SALVATION they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that bleſſed Eſtate which Mortals too greedy, and therefore too Credulous of Immortality, do, as I ſuppoſe, expect to injoy in the Elyſian Fields: But we mean by it certain and preſent Happineſs; and that this laſt ſignification is much more Noble and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58998:24"/>excellent then the other, and brings as we ſay, <hi>More Griſt to the Mill;</hi> from hence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that in the judgment of all Prudent men, <hi>Certain and preſent Goods, are to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before future and doubtful ones;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore likewiſe <hi>the Church has a Value for preſent things.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="demonstration">
                  <head>DEMONSTRATION.</head>
                  <p>Since by SALVATION nothing elſe is to be underſtood but the Welfare of the Church, <hi>as Def.</hi> 3. <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 1. and that the Church <hi>from the only Def. Epiſt.</hi> 1. is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Kingdom, which in fear and Spiritual obedience, and therefore <hi>as Def.</hi> 1. <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 1. in Religion only conſiſts; it muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity be thence Collected, that Salvation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be obtained without ſome Religion, which is what was to be Demonſtrated.</p>
                  <p>The force and power of this Period is ſo Firm and Evident, that not only the wiſeſt Law-givers and Founders of Republicks have in all Ages obſerved it, but even Boys are at this day Taught in the Schools, that no Earthly Governments can Subſiſt, unleſs they be founded upon, or at leaſt Bordered
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58998:25"/>about with Religion: And yet ſome trivial writers of Politicks (of which ſort of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, whole Shoals have in this Age been Bred in your <hi>Germany,</hi> as our moſt Eminent <hi>Richlieu</hi> uſed to ſay) have even to Loathing dictated out of <hi>Plate, Ariſtotle, Tully,</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi> whole Hundreds, nay, repeated Thouſands of patcht Syſtems for a Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Religion of Empires, which needed not have been ſo laboriouſly Incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated when no one can doubt of it, that is not abſolutely unexperienced in all things, and a ſtranger to all Common-wealths: <hi>For though</hi> (if I may ſpeak out of <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch) there are in all Stages of the Univerſal World,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Contra Coloſen.</note> 
                     <hi>Cities to be found wanting Walls, Learning, Laws, Houſes, Goods, Money, and Ignorant of Schools and Theatres; yet a City wanting thoſe Temples of the gods, where Prayers, ſolemn Vows, and Oracles were uſed, where Sacrifices are made for good things, and evils endeavoured to be averted by holy things no man yet ever ſaw: I therefore think it were eaſier to Build a City without a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>un, then that that City ſhould either gather or ſubſiſt, where the Opinion of the gods is utterly taken away.</hi> And 'tis but this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58998:25"/>
                     <hi>Savayedra</hi> meant when bluſhing to ſay over again what had been ſo often ſaid, he choſe rather to paint the Pillars of the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Floating in the Air, unleſs they were knit together by a <hi>Baſis</hi> of Religion. And the ſame thing though more newly and brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as he does many things elſe) ſays our <hi>Montaigne: Toute Police a un Dieu a ſa Tete,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſſais l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> 
                     <hi>All Police has a god at the head of it:</hi> To wit, <hi>It has ever been the Buſineſs of the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt and moſt Prudent men to deceive the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in matters of Religion,</hi> as St. Auſtine in his de Civ. Dei lib. iv. cap. 23. very well noted: For <hi>that all Actions might be made more venerable, they are to be referred to God,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Counſel of <hi>Campanella de Monar. Hiſp.</hi> cap. 9. <hi>for as much as all have a greater value for Divine, then humane Power,</hi> as was rightly obſerved by the moſt wiſe <hi>Machiavel</hi> Counſellor to his holineſs Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VI. in his Diſcourſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, Lib. 1.11. Nor if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Nature of men, can things be otherwiſe ſwayed, for all men are by Nature equal, as <hi>Hobbs de Cive.</hi> has rightly obſerved, and therefore as well out of a ſenſe of that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58998:26"/>Natural Equality, as out of a General Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition common to all Mortals, man does not ſo eaſily ſubject himſelf to Man as to God. But that Man (compelled to it by unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble neceſſity) may live in Society, he ties himſelf by certain Covenants and Laws: but thoſe Laws are onely armed againſt external actions, which muſt be proved by certain Reaſons and Circumſtances, ſo that not ſo much wickedneſs, as the diſcovery of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, not ſo much malice, as imprudence ſeems to be puniſhed. <hi>Whoever therefore can cloſely commit Injuries, Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Fr. in ad Ant. Fabri de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. reg.</note> 
                     <hi>Rapines, Murthers, will certainly care little for humane Laws, unleſs there be another Law which does inwardly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend its Threats even to the Soul of the Sinner.</hi> Hence <hi>Polybius,</hi> after he had told us, <hi>that the care of Religion and Superſtition was ſo much increaſed among the Romans,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Superſtition is increaſed unto admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſays he; and then, as though out of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found darkneſs he eſpied through a narrow creviſe, ſome diſtant light approaching, he adds, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58998:26"/>
                     <hi>I can think it done for no other end then to pleaſe the People, for the multitude are always various, full of unlawful deſires, precipitate in anger, and thence eaſily dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to fury; whence it comes to paſs that the Rabble are no way to be compelled, but by terrors not made manifeſt, or ſome horrible Bugbear fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi> Thus that Politick Scribler, whom if any one will not believe, he is ſurely to be condemned, not onely faſting and next his heart to ſwallow down the Monitions of <hi>Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> (for that Book is too ſmall) but even all the weighty Politicks of the R. F. Fryar <hi>Adam Runken,</hi> with all his Notes and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendixes, and the univerſal Common Places of the <hi>Germans.</hi> But enough! Return we to our purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>If then to the eſtabliſhing and preſerving of any Empire whatſoever, Religion be ſo neceſſary, how much more is it requiſite in ours, which is altogether ſacred and ſpiritual, &amp; not adminiſtred by profane men, but by our moſt Holy Pope. <hi>By Religion,</hi> ſays the often by us prais'd <hi>Thomas, the Pope rules over all Europe, Aſia, Africa and America, and in a word over
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58998:27"/>all the Chriſtians of this World, for thoſe who ſhine with the Majeſty of Religion cannot be reſiſted.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De M. H. C. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Take notice of Samuel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Id. C. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>who placed Saul on the Throne, and again Electing David, depoſed him. But what has not the Pope both dared and done in this Kind. Look upon Moſes, who alone with the Levites and Prieſts took Arms againſt the Rebellious Children of Iſrael and their Princes, who with their Wives exceeded the number of a million; and yet with the Arms of one Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Tribe, he ſlew in one day three and thirty thouſand men.</hi> Of theſe Prieſts it might truly be ſaid, That in their hands <hi>the word of God is quick and powerful, and ſharper then a two-edged Sword piercing even to the dividing aſunder of Soul and Spirit, and of the Joynts and Marrow,</hi> as ſays a certain nameleſs Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> Cap. 4.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>PROPOSITION II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>But Natural Religion is not ſufficient for Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58998:27"/>
                  <head>EXPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>BY Natural Religion we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>A comprehenſion of the Knowledge of ſome Superiour and Inviſible Power,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Def. un.</note> 
                     <hi>whether begotten at the ſame time with the Mind of Man, or collected from Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or a certain way of reaſoning of the Univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Things.</hi> Theſe Heads are by our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple termed <hi>Les cinque points du Catechiſme des Deiſtes,</hi> The Five Points of the Catechiſm of the Deiſts; by the Germans, <hi>Du funff Haupſtuct der Allgemeinen Naturlichen Religion.</hi> Of our ſide they have among others been Explained by the Venerable Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Garaſſus,</hi> but among the Hereticks by <hi>Herbert</hi> in his Fundamental Divinity, in two Books, one containing that of the <hi>Laicks,</hi> the other the Religion of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> of which Treatiſes, the firſt was Midwif'd into the World by a Man above all Praiſe and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and whoſe own Name is not to be named by us; but the other by that <hi>Belgian Heretick and a half,</hi> whom you know, the moſt ingenious <hi>Iſaac Voſsius.</hi> But the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles are muſtred up in this Order:</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58998:28"/>
                     <item>I. <hi>There is ſome Supreme Deity.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>That Deity ought to be Worſhipped.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>Virtue joyn'd with Piety, is the Beſt Rule of Divine Worſhip.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>IV. <hi>Sin is to be Repented of.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>V. <hi>Rewards and Puniſhments are to be given after this Life.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Theſe Five Axioms, and therefore <hi>all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion,</hi> we deny to be ſufficient for Salvation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="demonstration">
                  <head>DEMONSTRATION.</head>
                  <p>IT does not from thoſe Five now Rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Heads of Natural Religion, follow that all mortal men owe obedience to the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> For any one may believe,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That there is ſome Supreme Deity,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he do not believe any other beſides Kings and Princes, Vicar to that Deity, or that it has an Univerſal or Spiritual Head ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtant upon earth.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He <hi>may likewiſe believe that Deity ought to be worſhipped,</hi> and yet not from thence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come perſwaded that our Pope's Buttocks or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58998:28"/>Toes (for ſo it muſt be when all of him is alike holy) are to be kiſſed, or he to be ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Elevation at the Altar.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He may believe <hi>that Virtue joyn'd with Piety is the beſt Rule of Divine Worſhip,</hi> and yet doubt whether all Virtue conſiſts in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality to the Clergy, or whether all Piety be diſcharged in a blind Obedience to the Church.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He may believe <hi>Sin is to be repented of,</hi> though he be utterly ignorant of Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Penance, nor ever thought that Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was to be bought from the Prieſt with a ſacred Sheckle.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Laſtly, He may believe <hi>that there are Rewards and Puniſhments after this life,</hi> though perhaps he may judge that ſpeech of <hi>Sincerus Actius</hi> to Pope <hi>Clement,</hi> rather poetical than ſincere,
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Magne Parens cuſtoſque hominum, cui jus datur uni</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Claudere coeleſtes &amp; reſerare fores.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mans Guardian-Parent, to whom's onely given</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A right to ſhut and ope the Gates of Heaven.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58998:29"/>Therefore by the <hi>ſingle definition of this Propoſition, and Def.</hi> 3. <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 1. Natural Religion is not ſufficient for Salvation, which is what was to be demonſtrated.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="corollary">
                  <head>COROLLARY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore it does not appear from the Light of Nature onely, That the Pope of Rome is Lord of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, nor is this Myſtery reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all Nations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THere are which object all the Oracles and Auguries of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> by which the Eternity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Power, has been from the moſt Ancient of times propheſied and foretold. Yet I muſt confeſs that moſt Ancient Prophecy of <hi>Homers</hi> in his <hi>Illiads,</hi> concerning the Original of the City of <hi>Rome</hi> ſeems to me more wonderful then all the four or twelve Oracles of the Hebrew Prophets.
<q>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nunc autem Trojana Aeneas Sceptra tenebit,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Et Nati Natorum &amp; qui naſcentur ab ipſis.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58998:29"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Trojan Eueas ſhall the Scepter ſway.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And to his Childrens Children all obey.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> For <hi>Jupiter</hi> to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>— <hi>Nec metas rerum nec tempora ponit,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Imperium ſine fine dedit</hi> —</l>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Neither to bounds of things nor time,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Their endleſs Empire did confine.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> As <hi>Maro</hi> afterwards Sung. But not by Men only; but even by Women did theſe South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying Spirits foretel the Eternity of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Dominion. Let us read thoſe of the <hi>Erinnian</hi> Poeteſs; which the nearer to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Delphick Majeſty, we will firſt rehearſe in the Greek Tongue.
<q>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58998:30"/>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                     </q> Which in the Latine Tongue runs thus:
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Filia o Martis mihi Roma Salve,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aureo Regina decora cultu,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Quae vel in terra</hi> ſtabiles Olympi</l>
                        <l>Incolas arces.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nam dedit foli Tibi cana Parca.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Regium ſceptrum</hi> minime atterendum,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ut potens rerum domineris una,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Imperiteſque.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ipſa quae gandet variare cuncta,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Reſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> transformans Hominum Vetuſtas</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Spirat haec uni tibi ſemper auram a</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Puppe ſecundam.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> And in Engliſh may ſignifie thus:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Rome Mar's <hi>daughter Hail to me,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Of Gold, O Queen, thy deckings be.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Thou who on Earth poſſeſſeſt powers</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>As firm as the Olympick towers.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58998:30"/>
                           <l>
                              <hi>To thée fate only gave to bear,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>A Scepter can féel no impair.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>That yielding to thy powerful ſway,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Whilſt thou command'ſt, all might obey.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Time which delights the World to range,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And ſubjects Men and things to change:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Finding his power o're thée to fail,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Blows with a conſtant proſperous gale.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> For out of the <hi>Charonenſian</hi> Augury, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Fortune, Winged and Wandring, and now haunting the <hi>Aſſyrians;</hi> now the <hi>Medes, Perſians, Macedonians</hi> and <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> and forſaking them all, at <hi>Tiber</hi> laid down her Wings; and leaving her Voluble Globe, entred the City as a perpetual Inhabitant.</p>
                  <p>But above all, that <hi>Venuſian</hi> Poet deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly raviſhes us with an extream of Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who actuated with that Aetherial Spirit wherewith he was poſſeſt, foretels not only the Perpetuity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, but of our Papacy.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Non omnis moriar, multa<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>
                        </hi>
                        <note place="margin">lib. 3. od. ult.</note> 
                        <hi>pars mei</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vitabit Libitinam: uſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ego poſtera</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58998:31"/>
                     <l>Creſcam laude recens, DUM CAPITOLIUM</l>
                     <l>SCANDET CUM TACITAVIRGINE PONTIFEX.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I ſhan'c all die, my better part can't fade,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But with freſh praiſe the future World ſhall fill,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So long as</hi> POPES SHALL WITH THE SILENT MAID,</l>
                     <l>MOUNT UP UNTO THE CAPITOLIAN HILL.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>That is, <hi>for ever;</hi> which laſt words, a <hi>French</hi> Paraphraſt, much more pleaſant then the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable <hi>Marolius,</hi> very pregnantly rend red thus: <hi>Tandis que le Pontiff montera au Chateas de St. Ange quelque Religieuſe, que le laiſſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> faire &amp; ne dira mot, c'eſt a dire, tandis que le monde durera. As long as the Pope ſhall in the Caſtle of St.</hi> Angelo, <hi>mount ſome Nun, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhall let him do it, and not ſay a word;</hi> that is, <hi>as long as the world endures.</hi> Upon which place a very late Comentator adviſes, that not only the lives of the Popes, but of the Ladies of <hi>Marozia, Theodora, Vannocia</hi> and <hi>Olympia,</hi> ſhould be made inſpection into not indeed as they were writ by the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> but as lately ſet forth at <hi>Lyons,</hi> by the R. P. <hi>Fra Franciſcus Carriere Aptenſis Minoritae Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. D. Theol.</hi> Our ſingular good friend
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58998:31"/>and whom out of reſpect we name.</p>
                  <p>There are therefore that imagine, that a man attentive and deſirous of Salvation, may eaſily, out of theſe and ſuch like Oracles of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> collect that the Eternity &amp; Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the papal Empire, and therefore that the power of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, may become known to Mortals from <hi>the very Light of Nature.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But nevertheleſs, whoever they are that object ſuch things againſt the truth of our Corollary, do (in my opinion) much fail in their Judgment. For firſt, Thoſe Oracles are no way to be aſcribed to the univerſal light of Nature; but either to the cunning of ſome few, or chance; And ſmell rather, of the ingenuity of the Readers and Interpreters, then of the Authors; nor do they at all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain to natural Religion, but to the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the Doctrine of Devils;</hi> that is, the choiceſt, and moſt powerful part of the myſtical Conclave. Moreover, though they ſhould praeſignifie ſome <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and in that, the Eternity of the Sacerdotal Order; yet they leaſt of all por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that Monarchy which our <hi>Vice-Chriſt</hi> extends into almoſt all Regions of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58998:32"/>for this is a Myſtery hid from all Ages, <hi>and only revealed in theſe latter times, which never eyes before ſaw, nor ears heard; neither entred it into the heart of man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive;</hi> for between that prophane Empire of Kings, Conſuls and Ceſars; to which old <hi>Rome</hi> was obnoxious: and this of ours, lies a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Pit, and that is as much outreached by this,
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Longius terraeplaga quam remoto</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Diſt at Olympo.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                     <q>—<hi>As Heaven is from Earth,</hi> —</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Elegantly has the Author of the <hi>Nipotiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma di Roma,</hi> explained this difference, which the <hi>R. F. Sempercus</hi> three days ago ſent me a Copy of to read, out of which, doubting it may not be come to your hands, I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted theſe few things to be referred to Rome <hi>ſeemed born to rule over the World;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Il Nipotiſmo di Roma p. 1. lib. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>which may be ſaid with good reaſon, ſince it has ruled, and do's at preſent rule. But in the time that</hi> Rome <hi>was a Commou-wealth; in the time that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58998:32"/>governed in</hi> Rome: Rome <hi>never aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Command over Conſciences; nor in any time obliged the Souls of Men to pay ſo great a tribute to the Vatican. But the Popes (quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) confound together Spiritual Rule, &amp; Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Living, to make one body of theſe two Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and applying themſelves more to the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual then the Temporal, oblige both Princes and People to pay them ſo exact an Obedience, that the memory of it terrifies the very thoughts and ſoul. That power of the Popes, to ſhut the Gates of Heaven at their Will, and open thoſe of Hell at their Pleaſure, obliges People to forget the Obedience due to their Prince, and Proſtrate themſelves with Reverence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Feet. That Common-wealth which governed the World by Policy; The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperours who Lorded it with Arms: Thoſe Tyrants who trampled on it with Tyranny, never Dived into ſuch hidden Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes, nor knew how to Humble People to their Devotion, as they are at this day Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</hi> So far He: From all which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, how vain it is that ſome affirm, That the univerſal Monarchy of our Pope may be diſcovered by the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. We ſhall in the next place proceed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58998:33"/>to other things.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <salute>In the mean time, moſt Reverend Fathers, we bid you moſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily Farewell.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> from the Convent. <hi>Major,</hi> 
                  <date>the Ides of <hi>November,</hi> 1666.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="letter">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:58998:33"/>
            <head>
               <hi>JANUS ALEXANDRUS FERRARIUS OF THE</hi> AUGUSTIN ORDER. HIS Fourth Epiſtle Concerning the Uſefulneſs and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Faith.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Right Reverend <hi>ADRIAN and PETER of WALENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Reverend Men,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>ALmoſt at the firſt building of the City began the uſe of Martial Strenaeor Newyears-Gifts, under the Authority of King</hi> Tatius, <hi>who firſt made wreaths of the happy Tree in the ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuan Grove wearing them as happy Omens to the New-year. The Name it ſelf declares the thing for men ſtrenuous for their Virtue here uſed to meet, and therefore ſuch Cognizances are due
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58998:34"/>to you, whoſe divine Soul is a greater teſtimony of the Vigilancy, then the Omen can Expect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. x. Ep. 35.</note> Pardon the words of <hi>Symmachus,</hi> wherewith he of old complimented the Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Valentine, Theodoſ.</hi> and <hi>Arcads.</hi> but which we to the moſt Excellent worth of your moſt Reverend Perſons, with an ampler Right and greater Merit, have now applied, who have hitherto ſo dexterouſly laboured in ſo <hi>ſtrenuous</hi> a work; not for the ſake of any profane Empire, but for the Principality of the moſt holy <hi>Roman</hi> Church: For it was you <hi>who at the command of his Holineſs our Lord</hi> Alexander <hi>the</hi> VII. <hi>being then Apoſtolical Nuncio to the Region of the</hi> Rhine (<hi>upon which there is now Prayers and Peace in the Caſtle of</hi> Gondolpho) firſt brought forth of your Armory, Darrs of a clear new Frame, and to Ancient Mortals unknown; to wit, the SHIELD of ASSISTANCE, and the SWORD of GLORY, <hi>which what terror they ſtruck into the Proteſtants, Evangelicks, Reformiſts (or by what Names ſoever you will have them diſtinguiſhed) ſufficiently appears from the Loud Clamours and Lamentable Howlings
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58998:34"/>wherewith they every where fill'd the Air:</hi> So that about the very ſame time (and it was now almoſt the three and fortieth year of this Century) the <hi>Catti</hi> beyond <hi>Taunus</hi> and <hi>Meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bocus,</hi> being ſtirred up to Arms, made lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Clamours, placing their Garriſons againſt the <hi>Ubii,</hi> whoſe ſeats you then Inhabited, with ſo much affright, as if they had feared an utter deſtruction from the revived <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus,</hi> or <hi>Silius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is not only for your <hi>ſtrenuity</hi> that the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church owes you theſe <hi>Strena's,</hi> or Newyears-gifts, but for that likewiſe you lately on the Calends of <hi>January,</hi> made a preſent by-way of Newyears-gift of theſe your Arms, gnawn indeed a little with Ruſt, but yet new Clean'd and Poliſh'd, to the moſt Venerable Paſtours of the Arch-biſhopricks of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and <hi>Collogne,</hi> and thoſe who had the Care of Souls; withall Exhorting them that that New year, they with new minds ſhould ſubdue Hereticks, and if they muſt leſs publickly and ſolemnly Triumph over them, yet at leaſt in their Pavilions do it by Feſtival Dances; for the Laws of Newyears-gifts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be ſent to the Givers, as out of the old Inſtitutes of Gifts;</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:58998:35"/>Hoc damus alternis accepimuſque die,</q>
            <q>Theſe we alternately Give and Receive.</q>
            <p>Since then the uſe of that Gift is common to all, it belongs likewiſe to me, and leaſt both by others and my ſelf, I ſhould be thought ungrateful to you, moſt Reverend men; I thought fit, as well for the defence of the Publick ſafety, as for your ſingular Liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to addreſs ſome ſmall preſent to you; not clad in Gold, ſince our Monaſterial Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty deprives of the honour of enjoying that rich Mettal, but ſuch as my ſmall Stock will afford; this little Paper, to which I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figned ſome things already begun and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to you, as Demonſtrations of the Catholick faith.</p>
            <p>In the progreſs of which, that we may come to the thing it ſelf there now follows in the order of our deſign.</p>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>PROPOSITION, III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>To purchaſe Salvation, or to Eſtabliſh and maintain the Regal Papacy of</hi> Rome, <hi>there is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58998:35"/>beſides Natural Religion, another required which is called Supernatural.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>EXPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>That by the <hi>attaining Salvation,</hi> nothing elſe is meant then the Eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Royal Roman Papacy,</hi> plainly appears from <hi>Prop.</hi> 1. wherefore we ſhall uſe theſe Terms in the ſame ſence promiſcuouſly, which it will be ſufficient to have given this Advice of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Def. un.</hi> But by <hi>Supernatural Religion,</hi> we underſtand <hi>that maſs of Rites and Tenents which not from the common and uſual Dictates of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but out of ſome ſingular and immediate Revelation of a Diety is made known to ſome one in particular, or to very few Mortals, and by them ſaid to be Propogated to others.</hi> Which deſcription if you compare with <hi>Def.</hi> 1. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po.</hi> 2. you will eaſily find what is the difference between theſe two kinds of Religion: Yet this Religion which we call <hi>Supernatural,</hi> may likewiſe be termed <hi>Civil;</hi> for it is either on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deviſed for the Conſtituting and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the City, or if it truly come from God and he being indeed the Author of it, it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtined
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58998:36"/>to a more Sublime and Eternal end, yet it conduces no leſs to this: I might add that it commands a more punctual obſervance of Civil Laws, and may therefore in that ſence likewiſe be called <hi>Civil;</hi> but ſince that Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation ſtrikes not any Religious Venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the Hearers, I had rather wave it as well as that of <hi>Preternatural,</hi> as which, has me-thinks, ſomething an uncouth and hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſound. We have therefore ſaid <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural,</hi> as a word compoſed of a nobler Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, and which Imprints a loftier <hi>Idaea</hi> in our Souls.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="demonstration">
                  <head>DEMONSTRATION.</head>
                  <p>Since by <hi>Prop.</hi> 1. to the Conſtituting ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Empire, ſome Religion is neceſſary; but the Natural by <hi>Prop.</hi> 2. is not ſufficient, it is expedient that to the Supplement and Aſſiſtance of the other ſhould be added which is called <hi>Supernatural,</hi> which is what is to be Demonſtrated.</p>
                  <p>That Religion ſimply (which Nature has taught to all, ſcarce ever contented any one City, but either they Illuſtrated it with the ſplendor of Ceremonies, or augmented it with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58998:36"/>the acceſſion new Tenents and Opinions, either derived by Tradition from others, or deviſed out of their own Brain; ſo that if the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal conſent of all Mankind be ſufficient to Eſtabliſh a truth, it may from hence be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively concluded, that there is a neceſſity of a Supernatural Religion; but if a more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomn and diligent Pomp in Divine Worſhip be requiſite to the maintaining of any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, none can be ſo ſtupid but to foreſee how abundantly it is neceſſary to our Empire, as that wherein altogether conſiſts in the Inſtitution, Defence, and Amplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy Conclave.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <head>PROPOSITION IV,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Supern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tural Religion ought to be ſo conſtituted, that in it ſelf and in the Nature of its Principles, it may Level at Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>EXPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>There are two kinds of <hi>means,</hi> ſome <hi>from
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58998:37"/>themſelves and out</hi> of their own <hi>inclination</hi> are carried to ſome end, and others beſide their Nature are wreſted to it by ſome art. Thoſe are Smooth, Native, Genuine and Streight: Theſe Violent, Artificial, Counterfeit and Crooked. Thoſe therefore are more Facile and more Firm. Theſe more Difficult and Unſtable, and which though never ſo much Bowed to our purpoſe, yet often on the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den leave us, and briefly return to their own Nature. Wherefore as they alſo ſay in the Schools:
<note place="margin">Hypoth. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntoſoph.</note> 
                     <hi>The Excellency of Means conſiſts only in the relation and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency to the end.</hi> Becauſe, <hi>'Tis that from which they receive all Lovelineſs, Order and Meaſures.</hi> It muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be gathered, that thoſe things are beſt and moſt perfect which are deſtined from their own Nature and Internal Principles, to the obtaining of any end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="demonstration">
                  <head>DEMONSTRATION.</head>
                  <p>Since by <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. Supernatural Religion is a means neceſſary to Salvation, and out of the <hi>Hypoth, Ontoſoph.</hi> thoſe means are beſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58998:37"/>which by their own proper Nature are carried to ſome end, it neceſſarily follows ſuch a Supernatural Religion is to be eſtabliſhed, which in it ſelf, and the <hi>genius</hi> of its Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, tends to Salvation; which is what was to be demonſtrated.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="proposition">
               <head>PROPOSITION V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where therefore either by the Ignorance, Imprudence, Malice or Studies dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from ours of our Anceſtors; any ſuch Supernatural Religion, has got ſway, as do's not conduce to our Solvation, 'tis expedient it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>EXPLICATION <hi>AND</hi> DEMONSTRATION.</head>
                  <p>When even the <hi>Freſhmen</hi> of the <hi>Ramiſts</hi> can tell us, <hi>that the means are only for the end, therefore that taken away they ceaſe:</hi> There is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58998:38"/>no need of a more ample Explication or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration.</p>
                  <p>Certainly that Camel-driver <hi>Mahomet,</hi> though rude and untaught in other things, was not ignorant of theſe; who out of his love to <hi>Chadiga,</hi> being to ſeek out Empire at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of his <hi>Magot;</hi> when among the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Tribes of his envyers, he perceived the Idolatry of the <hi>Korathites,</hi> the Religion of the <hi>Saboeans,</hi> the Superſtition of the <hi>Jews;</hi> and the Faith of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to be quite different from his purpoſe; he aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all, and eſtabliſhed a new form of Worſhip, made up of a commixture of their principle Tenents, with the addition of ſome new ones. Nor was it for any other end that the <hi>Perſians,</hi> rejecting <hi>Mahomets</hi> Doctrine, have more lately followed, the Propheſies of <hi>Haly;</hi> but only, becauſe they believed one common worſhip with the Enemies of their Empire, to be dangerous; and with better Wiſdom, adjudged an <hi>intire Wall</hi> was to be erected between them, at leaſt, out of a new trimm'd up Religion.</p>
                  <p>But what need is there of reciting Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples from Infidels, when in this matter we may praiſe God as the prime Author? Who
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58998:38"/>when he was about by <hi>Moſes</hi> to erect his <hi>Theocracy</hi> over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not only aboliſhed Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and the diſcordant Opinions of right reaſon; but even thoſe <hi>Noachides</hi> lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to us by <hi>Seldens</hi> admirable induſtry; compoſing a Religion full of new Precepts and Ceremonies; and preſcribing that ſort of Worſhip, whoſe ſeveral Heads, though they refer to myſtical ends, yet do as high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tend to the Service of the Politicks, and what is called <hi>Reaſon</hi> of <hi>State.</hi> And yet that Religion, though eſtabliſhed by Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and made Dreadful by many Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and Prodigies, was afterwards not a little altered by <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> when ſnatching away the Ten Tribes from <hi>Judah,</hi> he found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a new Empire, and conſtituted a new ſeat of Religion.</p>
                  <p>But of theſe things, when I can obtain both that <hi>Indulgence</hi> from my <hi>Superiours,</hi> and that leaſure agreeable to me and my temper, I have a deſign more largely to diſcourſe, taking the Argument of my Treatiſe from <hi>Maimonidis More Hannev. part</hi> 3. <hi>cap</hi> 26. and the <hi>Diſput. Regis Coſareorum, part.</hi> 4. <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. Either of which Books, if you do not abhor (for the Character of Damnation,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58998:39"/>ſet upon them by your <hi>Richleran</hi> Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) yet to read over, we have them in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary of our Monaſtery; and that (at your Service) in the Latine Tongue, ſet forth by that famous Interpreter among the Judai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Calviniſts, <hi>Buxtorfius</hi> the Son, lately indeed ſlipt hence; but both whoſe, and whoſe Fathers glory, <hi>the half Heretick Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vignius</hi>'s our Schollers, do report plentifully to bloſſom forth in the Nephew, ſo that if any Scruple happen in the reading them, you have yet one living to remove all doubts.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="proposition">
               <head>PROPOSITION VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore that Supernatural Religion which do's not conduce to Salvation, ſhould immediately, at one stroke, and with open violence be deſtroyed; Provided that may ſafely and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently be done. If not, by ſlow and gentle Arts it must leaſurely and by piece meal be changed; ſtill keeping the ſame outward face and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58998:39"/>favour, until it be prrfectly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for the attaining Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>EXPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>Two ways principally may things be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; either by manifeſt and open ſtrength and violence, or by cloſe proceedings and ſecret wiles. The firſt way is moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently applyed, when thoſe things we defire to root out conſiſt in few, and thoſe ſolid parts, and obvious to every eye; ſo that they neither admitting of ſundry degrees, nor va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying themſelves into diverſe modes, ſcarce can ſeparately be diſſolved, or ſecretly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd; Such things it were more adviſedly to overthrow all at once, and at a ſingle blow: For ſhould you attempt to ruine them with a ſlow and gentle Arm, the moſt you could do, would be unſeaſonably to betray your own Counſel, ſtirring up others, who at firſt onſet will cry out upon you for a Corrupter and an Innovator; and more curiouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving every thing, contrive ſtronger En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins of reſiſtance. But then here, firſt of all, you muſt diligently conſult whether you
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58998:40"/>are furniſhed with Aids, and fortified with Strength, ſufficient at one claſh to Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, Oppreſs and Break all Oppoſing Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for if ſuch powers be in the leaſt want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, another way is to be try'd; that with a ſilent ſtep, and careful motion, by Stratagem you may arrive at your end. And this laſt way is chiefly to be practiſed when thoſe things we are about to aboliſh, conſiſt of many parts; and thoſe ſo various and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible, that they may be increaſed and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, ſtretched and looſned, and varied into ſo many ſhapes, that though they are in truth changed; either they ſhall ſeem ſtill in their ſame State, or to Vulgar Eyes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear not much receded from it: For if you would remove all thoſe parts at once, or at one violent puſh, ſubſtitute all new things in their Room, it can never be done without raiſing mighty Troubles, and ſtirring up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Confuſions; from whence you will never get free, but either with ignominy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to a diſhonourable retreat, or contract to your ſelf moſt Peſtilent Envy. And this is likewiſe chiefly to be obſerved, when thoſe things you ſtrive to pull up, have taken deep Root,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58998:40"/>
                     <q>Et jam per longas invaluere moras.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>For though at all other times, yet eſpecially in this caſe, vehement and ſudden changes are moſt dangerous; and therefore we have likewiſe ſaid in our <hi>Propoſition,</hi> that that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Religion which is already grown powerful, but is unproper for our ends, ought to be quaſht at one ſtroke; PROVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DED THAT MAY SAFELY AND CONVENIENTLY BE DONE; otherwiſe you muſt tread another path much ſafer, and not only to things, but to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings of Mankind more agreeable: For we are ſo formed by Nature, that we had rather be with Flatteries allured and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvented, then forceably compelled; And we more willingly admit gentleneſs, though Treacherous and Deceitful, then any open Violence. Beſides, whenever by our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence, the buſineſs is brought to an Iſſue; though we afterwards diſcover the deceit, we for the moſt part chooſe rather to acquieſce under the preſent ſtate of affairs, then ſeek to recall what was before with difficulty and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of event.</p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:58998:41"/>
                  <p>But this laſt Method contains two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, One, <hi>That things be changed leaſurely and cloſely;</hi> the other, <hi>That they ſtill retain the ſame outward Face and Favour:</hi> Which two, if rightly obſerved, will produce incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible advantages; and which if you will hearken to St. <hi>Aquinas,</hi> ſeem to exceed the Omnipotency of the moſt high; For by them it comes to paſs, <hi>that the ſeveral parts, though at length all taken away, yet the whole, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, remains intire;</hi> which yet the <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> and <hi>Occamiſts</hi> with one conſent teach us, implies a contradiction, as I remember long ſince to have heard from my Maſter, of bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed memory D. <hi>Raconis,</hi> of the <hi>Navarr</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. But we will follow the <hi>Scotiſts;</hi> and then thoſe to whom, as you have taught, it were to be wiſhed that the defence of the Catholick Religion, were hereafter to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, rather then to the Divines, to wit, <hi>the Lawyers;</hi> for thus <hi>Alfenus,</hi> l. 76. F. <hi>de Judiciis. Proponebatur, ex his Judicibus qui in eandem rem dati eſſent nonnullos cauſa audita ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſatos eſſe,
<note place="margin">In Exam. Princip.</note> in<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> eorum locum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os eſſe ſumptos,</hi> &amp;c.
<q>It was propoſed out of thoſe Judges imployed in the ſame thing,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58998:41"/>ſome after the hearing of the Cauſe were diſmiſſed, and others taken in their places; and it was queſtioned if the change of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Judges, made the ſame thing, or another Judgment. I anſwer, that if not only one or another; but if all the Judges were changed, yet the matter would remain the ſame, and the Judgment the ſelf ſame it was before. Nor do's it only happen in this, that though the parts be altered, the thing is adjudged to be the ſame, but in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things; For that Legion is ſtill accounted the ſame, from which many have departed, and others have ſupplyed their places; and the People at this time think it the ſame that it was an hundred years ago, though not one that was then in it be alive. In the like manner, a Ship, though it be ſo often rebuilt, that there is not one Plank in it but what is new, is notwithſtanding judged to be the ſame Ship; for if any one ſhall think the changing of parts, changes the thing, we by the ſame reaſon muſt not be our ſame ſelves, which within a year we were; for as Philoſophers ſay, we conſiſt of certain minute Particles, which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually give place in our Bodies to others
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58998:42"/>which inwardly ſucceed them; and this all our <hi>Interpreters adviſe,</hi> to be effected in things that ſucceſſively, and by parts, but not at once are wholly changed.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the ſame is delivered by the new Doctors of the Metaphyſicks, and by the Hereticks themſelves; among all whom we will make choice of <hi>Claubergius,</hi> a man dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Heretical, as both infected with <hi>Carteſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm</hi> and <hi>Calviniſm;</hi> and who under that Title (had the <hi>Tutoberg</hi> Sepultures been in our power) was to have been burnt; but yet, whom our moſt worthy <hi>Clerſelerius,</hi> and the moſt friendly <hi>Rovraeus</hi> have given great praiſes to, for the ſharpneſs of his Wit, and clearneſs of his Writing.</p>
                  <p>He therefore <hi>Ontoſoph.</hi> Sect. 294. <hi>Tota,</hi> inquit, <hi>haec diſputatio de eodemac di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſo,
<note place="margin">Edit ult.</note> potius ad modum cogitandi &amp; loquendi pertinet,</hi> &amp;c.
<q>All this diſputation (ſay's he) of the ſame or a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe thing, rather relates to the manner of thinking and ſpeaking, then to the things well conſidered in themſelves; whence the wiſe and vulgar, neither think nor ſpeak alike in this matter; nor indeed do wiſe men among themſelves, though it be made
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58998:42"/>evident by other examples then that of the Philoſophers diſpute concerning <hi>Theſeus's</hi> Ship, which may be read in <hi>Plutarch</hi> his <hi>Theſeus.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Sect. 295.</bibl> 
                     <hi>Si non ſimul &amp; ſemel, at paulatim &amp; ſenſim ſit mutatio facta,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  <q>If not together and at once, yet leaſurely, and by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, let the change be made; ſo that being ſcarce obſerved, it will for the moſt part be called the ſame. Thus Fire, which (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> well obſerves, <hi>lib. de juvent. cap,</hi> 5) continually is rouling and preſſing forward like a Flood, though by its ſwiftneſs it gets out of our ſight, is thought all night the ſame Fire, if fed with continual Fewel; but if the Fire be once quite extinguiſhed, and then again gets head, it is avouched to be another. If a Ship be at once deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all its parts, that is, reputed of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther number, which in its place is built of new Timber. But if a Ship be repaired in parts, and in progreſs of years becomes wholly changed, there are few men but will call it the ſame Ship: For Example, that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58998:43"/>of <hi>Theſeus,</hi> in which at laſt, there was not one Plank of the old Timber remaining. This reaſon of the ſelf ſame being, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds wholly from our careleſneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſideration, making us account a change leaſurely and ſlowly made, though it be as much a change, as when happening toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and at once, almoſt for none at all.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Sect. 296.</bibl> 
                     <hi>Licet omnia accidentia externa quae incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt in ſenſus mutentur, dummodo maneat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>variatum aliquod fundamentum ſaepe res eadem eſſe cenſetur,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  <q>Though all external ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents that preſent themſelves to the ſenſes may be changed, yet if any fundamental part remain unaltered, the thing is often judged to be the ſame. An Example we have in boyling or melted Wax, in reſpect of that is ſolid and hard, in which all the Senſibles are changed. Yet the extended and mutable ſubject remains ſtill endued with certain eſſential properties of Wax.</q>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:58998:43"/>
                     <bibl>Sect. 297.</bibl> 
                     <hi>Si manſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rint partes Principales, licet minus principales pereant, totum Judicatur idem,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  <q>If the more principal parts remain, though the leſs principal parts periſh, it ſhall be judged to be all the ſame: For Example, It will be called the ſame Houſe, whoſe foundation and walls are ſtanding, though all things elſe be deſtroy'd.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Sect. 298.</bibl> 
                     <hi>Si veltota mutetur materia dummodo forma quaedam eadem conſervetur, totum haud rar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur idem permanere,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  <q>Or though the whole matter be changed, yet if ſome form be preſerved, the whole is not rarely ſaid to remain: For Example, That is thought to be the ſame City or Univerſity now, which it was an hundred years ago; though now the Citizens are all other perſons then at that time they were. But how the word FORM is to be underſtood in ſuch things, can ſcarce be defined by a general concluſion; for if you call that City the ſame, becauſe it re tains
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58998:44"/>the ſame Laws and Priviledges, and Place. Yet though thoſe be in all or the moſt part changed, it will not be forthwith thought another. Academy's remain the ſame, though transferred elſewhere, as is done either in time of War or Plague; and the City may go out of the Town.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Sect. 299.</bibl> 
                     <hi>Omnis igitur identitas, quae rebus tribuitur, requirit aliquod fundamentum, quod vel reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra vel apparenter maneat immutatum,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  <q>Therefore every Identiry or ſameneſs, which is attributed to things, requires ſome Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, which muſt either really or ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remain unchangeable; whence it is either truly or apparently ſo, according to being, or according to ſaying only.</q>
                  <p>You will doubtleſs wonder <hi>Right Reverend Men,</hi> that we continue ſo long upon theſe <hi>Metaphyſical</hi> obſervations, unleſs your ſelves have already made the diſcovery; That here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>under lies hid the whole myſterions foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the thrice holy Monarchy, and that in theſe Cradles, from the firſt Infant Eſtate of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58998:44"/>the Church, that mighty Monſter firſt began to be nurſt up. Wherefore I think it well worth the pains, to adviſe that theſe things be diligently deliberated in our minds, being certainly perſwaded that the fuller we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, we ſhall the more fortunately and readily be verſed in all the reſt. Nor will there any great difficulty in the rectification of Religion intervene, when we ſhall from theſe principles have but indifferently learnt the arts of erecting Idols, and ſetting up of Images. And what may give the greater facility to this work is, that we have lately, by moſt beneficial induſtry, and exceedingly to the good of all Mankind, that art of laying on Colours, and diſpoſing a <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>us,</hi> moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently and neatly laid down in a certain Syſtem of Precepts; to which end likewiſe, and with leſs labour to be attain'd by us, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Examples of all humane actions do preſent themſelves, which we may imitate, as either the nature of things or ingenuity of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſhall ſuggeſt us the occaſions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="demonstration">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:58998:45"/>
                  <head>DEMONSTRATION.</head>
                  <p>Since by <hi>Prop.</hi> V. it apppears, that that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is not proper to the attaining Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, ought to be aboliſhed; and from what we have now explained, it is evident it cannot be aboliſhed, but either by Force or Art; it is neceſſary one of thoſe two ways, according to the condition of time and place be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which is what was to be Demonſtrated.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>I had many more things, but the Poſt is going, therefore
<salute>Farewell in the Lord.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> from the great <hi>Convent.</hi> 
                  <date>theſe <hi>Calends</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> from the year of the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins Child-bearing, MDCLxvii.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="letter">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:58998:45"/>
            <head>
               <hi>JANUS ALEXANDRUS FERRARI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S OF THE</hi> AUGUSTIN ORDER HIS Fifth Epiſtle, Concerning the Uſefulneſs and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Faith, To the Right Reverend <hi>ADRIAN and PETER of WALLENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Reverend Men,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe ſad fate of the <hi>BREVINGIAN</hi> Schollar, I heartily grieve for. I took care Yeſterday that all the Schollars at St. <hi>Mathurinus,</hi> ſhould Implore their Patron in Aſhes, and make a ſolemn Proceſſion for his Health, I often heard in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ere now, that he was troubled with a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or fainting and ſounding fits, but
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58998:46"/>never knew it was gone ſo far that his whole good mind was utterly infected. I conſulted our <hi>Guidon,</hi> who you know is a moſt Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Phyſitian, and who in words commanded me moſt friendly to ſalute you. I concealed the Patients name, only expoſing the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe with its Symptoms; he adviſed to let Blood in the <hi>Vena media,</hi> and then follow the ſame Rule of Phyſick, which <hi>Franciſcus Bartolettus,</hi> preſcribed thoſe afflicted with a <hi>Stentory.</hi> I went to another Phyſitian who believes the Diſeaſe may be only a ſimple Conſumption of the Underſtanding, yet fears leaſt it may next turn into a total, and therefore incurable <hi>Cachexy</hi> of the Brain. I hope better things, eſpecially if he could but once return to himſelf. Had he but that Medicine which we vulgarly call <hi>Antimony,</hi> but the <hi>French</hi> call in Latin <hi>Antimonachum,</hi> and which, as I have heard, is excellently well prepared by ſome of the Hereticks; nor do I believe, but that one in Orders may ſeek health from Hereticks, as well as Chriſtians receive it from <hi>Jews.</hi> But I will here ſtop, and no longer detain you with the unſavory Memory of the hard Fate of ſo friendly a man. I ſend you therefore a Dialogue which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58998:46"/>I Yeſterday received from <hi>Italy,</hi> of which what your thoughts are, let me know as ſoon as you can.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> from the great Convent <date>theſe Calends of <hi>May,</hi> MDCLxvii.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="dialogue">
                           <head>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN
<note n="*" place="margin">Sona <hi>the Church of Rome.</hi>
                              </note> 
                              <hi>SONA</hi> and <hi>ROPHAEUS.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>I Heard you were Tormented with a cruel Diſtemper, faireſt <hi>Sona,</hi> and therefore with that ſame Devotion wherewith I adore your Father and your Spouſe, I came hither to offer you my Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and become your Phyſitian.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Spona,</speaker>
                              <p>I owe you indeed many thanks for your kindneſs, moſt Experienced <hi>Rophaus,</hi> but for your coming to me upon ſuch an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion there was no neceſſity. Envious and Malicious men aſperſe my Fame, and among
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58998:47"/>the perverſeſt of them, thoſe wicked Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado's, <hi>Rethulus</hi> and <hi>Uſinulca,</hi> whom by th' Maſs, could I but catch, I would ſo Comb with a Faggot, that—</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>Pray be not angry ſweeteſt Lady.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>Who can be patient in ſuch a caſe as this, for canſt thou my <hi>Rophaeus,</hi> diſcover in my Face, or the whole Conſtitution of my Body, any thing that denies me to be in perfect Health?</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>Let me, I beſeech you, beg leave clearly and plainly to tell you what I think. When you were a tender Maid, you did not look ſo Beautiful as now: Your Face then was Swarthy, as if it had been Sun-burnt, and by reaſon of your frequent <gap reason="foreign">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap> or bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, your Body was leaner and drier, your Forehead was not then deckt with thoſe Curles, nor had you that Laſcivious Agility in your Carriage, the Arts and Curioſities of Dreſſing had not then paſt upon you; and I then remember to have ſeen you not clothed in Purple, nor ſhining in cloth of Gold, nor glittering in Gems; but Poor and Ragged, far below the glory of your Deſcent, and the Dignity of your Eſpouſals: But now I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold you more Stately and Magnificent.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58998:47"/>Thoſe more charming Allurements of your Eyes, that Exalted Countenance; That Lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Majeſtick Gate; That inticing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour of Body; That Splendour of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire; That Pride of Furniture, and that Throne Shining every where with Gold and Ivory, draw both the Eyes and Hearts of Specators, ſo that you ſeem to Sit here like a Goddeſs; yet all theſe things promiſe but little towards perfect Health. I know Women naturally love to hear themſelves praiſed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis poſſible I may ſeem Rude and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courtly thus to throw your Vices in your Teeth; but I hope both the Office of a Friend and a Phyſitian, will plead my Excuſe. When therefore, I moſt ſtedfaſtly regard you: I find (to ſpeak ingeniouſly) all theſe things Painted and Counterfeit, nor can I diſcern the flowers of Native Beauty, nor the lively and active Strength of Body; your Eyes dart forth I know not what kind of Venim, that their very Brightneſs ſeems infected with Contagion; thoſe Patches with which here and there you have beſpeckled your Face, do not ſo much ſerve to ſet off it's Complexion, as to cover Blemiſhes and hide Tokens of your Diſeaſe, and its apparent to every one
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58998:48"/>that <hi>Crimſon</hi> mixt with <hi>White,</hi> is rather the effects of <hi>Ceruſe</hi> and <hi>Minium,</hi> then a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Tincture of the Blood. There be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore ſo many manifeſt ſigns that you are infected with a foul Diſeaſe: Pray tell me when your Diſtemper firſt ſeized you?</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>As though I had taken notice of the hour.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>It will be very neceſſary that you tell me what time you began to be firſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with it, that I may know whether the Diſeaſe be Freſh, or Inveterate.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>And pray then, do you tell me too good Old man, From what hour you began to be thus unmannerly and importunate, or from what minute you began to grow Old?</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>From the very minute of my Birth.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>How can that be? That you ſhould be Young and Old together, when theſe two are contraries.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>Leave your Gibing, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of more moment in hand: But why do'ſt Laugh?</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>There comes into my head, a diſpute of my ſeventh Lover, he though the moſt decrepit of all Men, hotly contended Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day that he was young: He alledged that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58998:48"/>when none could determine the time, nor place wherein he began to grow Old or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in ſtrength, as no man could ſay that he did wax Old; ſo from thence he gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all men ought to eſteem him Young, and of a Juycy and intire Strength, and pleaſing himſelf with this way of Reaſoning, he col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected together all the ſtrength his Fancy could feed him withal, and addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more fervently to me, embracing me ſtreighter then ever <hi>Mars</hi> did his <hi>Venus,</hi> when <hi>Vulcan</hi> caught them together in a Net: But alaſs, poor wretch, he ſoon found his Nerves fail him.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>Very wittily, and from hence thou wouldſt argue thy ſelf a Virgin and in perfect health, becauſe you know not the hour when firſt this Diſtemper ſiezed you, and from what Coition you firſt received the ſeeds of Contagion.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>I muſt confeſs, I ſet not that down in my <hi>Kalender,</hi> nor do I remember the Age in which I either was a Virgin, or ceaſ'd to be ſo.
<note place="margin">Petron Arbiter.</note> For, <hi>Et infans cum Paribus inquinabar, &amp; ſubinde prodeuntibus annis majoribus me pue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris applicui, donec ad hanc Aetatem perveni.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58998:49"/>Vitulum puellam ſolebam tollere, quo facilius adulta taurum ſuſtinere poſſem.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>Yet did you appear holier then the holieſt Veſtals.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>'Tis true, I compoſed my Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to ſuch Baſhfulneſs and Modeſty, that it deceived even the ſevereſt Cenſurers, no leſs then <hi>Aretines Nanna,</hi> who ſo often ſold her Virginity.
<note place="margin">Aret. Region Par. 1. Gior. 3.</note> 
                                 <hi>Chi non vende un di queſti pretacci la meſſa novella, attaccando per ogni Citta police alle chieſe del ſuo eantarla.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>Tell me the truth. How couldſt thou fall into this courſe of Life, when thou wert deſcended from ſo holy a Father, deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſo holy a Spouſe, and brought up with ſuch ſolicitous Care and Diligence.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>Thou know'ſt, friendly <hi>Rophaeus,</hi> my Parents, and under what Covenants I was in my Infant years delivered by my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to my Spouſe, to be Educated accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his will and pleaſure; thou knoweſt with what mind he went to the Father, not deſigning before I was of perfect Age, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to me and carry me Home. Before he departed, he appointed ſeveral Inſtructers
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58998:49"/>over me and my Siſters, by whoſe care and exemplary Life we were ſtirred up to Piety and Chaſtty, and inſtructed in divers Tongues; whence it came to paſs that of my Siſters, ſome ſpoke <hi>Greek,</hi> others <hi>Perſian,</hi> others <hi>Arabick,</hi> and others, <hi>Aethiopian.</hi> He would not have us all Cohabit in the ſame place, and yet be ſubject to the <hi>Empire of one only Tutor,</hi> who ſhould Adminiſter to all our Welfare, and have a ſupreme Power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all our <hi>Inſtructors:</hi> He was a man of an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere inclination, who very roughly treated me and my Siſters, whether out of ſome conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed command of our Parents, who by Rigid Diſcipline would have our Chaſtities pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and all Laſciviouſneſs bridled; or out of a natural ſeverity and ill will conceived againſt us. He then lived at <hi>Valentia,</hi> where I was likewiſe bred up: Wherefore my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters when they had any Affairs to be negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated with our <hi>Tutor,</hi> made uſe of the care and diligence of my <hi>Inſtructors,</hi> and my own Recommendations, whereupon there accru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them a great Authority above others; and I, though the youngeſt, eaſily gained the upperhand of my Elders in all Ages. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, I carried my ſelf very ſtrictly, for
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58998:50"/>though tempted by many, and though I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly would have been profuſe in Luſt, I had not the liberty, unleſs very cloſely to play the Wanton; for I was watch'd over in the ſame manner which our <hi>Boccalinus</hi> teachesfrom the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> as the beſt way to mortifie the <hi>Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan</hi> Courſer: <hi>Che molte volte in un tempo medeſimo piu toſto ha voluto eſser calvalcato da doi Regi che da un ſolo: Which often at the ſame time had rather be rid by two Kings then one.</hi> Under this ſevere Diſcipline, I now arrived the third Luſtre of my Age, when my firſt <hi>Tutor</hi> dead, another ſucceeded; to wit, that great <hi>Quadratus,</hi> whom you knew, moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent to me and to my Siſters, and who to us and to our <hi>Inſtructers</hi> granted things which my Father and Spouſe would not have had granted, as from that time I knew. But he was ſo allured with the artifices of my <hi>Inſtructers,</hi> that leaving <hi>Valentia</hi> &amp; removing his Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Zantybium,</hi> he in a manner committed both himſelf &amp; me to his Arbitriment. Then being leſs reſtrained by the fear of our <hi>Tutor,</hi> webegan to live in a much more ſweet &amp; fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar manner, till my <hi>Inſtructers</hi> mind height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the mighty Riches came in from his Adminiſtrations, and by his growing Power
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58998:50"/>and Authority, he became at laſt ſo puft up, as to dare publickly to ſolicite me of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and to love me to the utmoſt Rites. He boaſted that in the abſence of my Spouſe he only was proper for me, and to that end com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to me my Fathers Teſtament, which ſparingly read to me he Explained to his own purpoſe. Often turning himſelf towards me; If (ſaid he) thy Spouſe had any love for thee, if he intended to confirm the Marriage Contract made between you, he had not gone away ſo ſuddenly to the Father, nor for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years left thee here alone, nor committed thee at firſt to ſo harſh a <hi>Tutor,</hi> nor command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee to be over-burthened with ſuch bitter Servitude, nor bound thee under ſuch ſtrict Laws, the obſervance of which is ſcarce Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on, or Exacted from the vileſt Slave. In ſhort, how heavy and troubleſome, how prodigious and ridiculous is that habit where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he, I think, only for a Laughing-ſtock would have thee Clad? <hi>The Girdle of Truth,</hi>
                                 <note place="margin">Eph. vi.</note> 
                                 <hi>the Bleſt-plate of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Shoes of the Preparation of the Goſpel of Peace, the Shield of Faith, the Helmet of Salvation, and the Sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> He will have to be your <hi>Wedding Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                                 <pb n="86" facs="tcp:58998:51"/>Who ever ſince the Memory of man, deſigned his beloved Spouſe ſuch a ſort of Attire? When <hi>Purple, and Scarlet,</hi>
                                 <note place="margin">Revel. xvii.</note> 
                                 <hi>and Gold, and precious Stones, and Pearls,</hi> are fitter for thee. Theſe things become a Virgin of thy Rank.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>The ſame then happened to thee which lately our Friend <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> writ me from <hi>France,</hi>
                                 <note place="margin">The fruitleſs Precaution.</note> had happened to <hi>Laura,</hi> a Noble woman of <hi>Spain.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>Pray tell the Story.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>There was among the Noblemen of that Kingdom one <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> a man of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent underſtanding and clear inſight into things, but more eſpecially Experienced in the Arts of Women, and how fickle both their Faith and Chaſtity is. He took care of the Education of <hi>Laura,</hi> a moſt Beautiful Virgin, whom he cauſed to be ſhut up in a Monaſtery, from the Society of all men, and to be Bred up under the ſtricteſt Diſcipline till ſhe arrived at her Sixteenth year of Age, when he eſpouſes her and carries her home; She was then altogether as ſimple as <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpina</hi> in <hi>Marinus,</hi> who did not ſo much as
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58998:51"/>know what Wantonneſs was; and <hi>Don Pedro</hi> told her, that Conjugal Faith &amp; Loyalty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in her ſtanding whole Nights by her Husband's Bed-ſide armed Cap-a-pee, with Helmet, Sword and Spear, watching her Husband whilſt he ſweetly ſlept. She wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly obeys him, being Ignorant of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Delight or Pleaſure, till within a few days <hi>Don Pedro</hi> is called to Court. And ſhe being left at home alone, is viſited by a Neighbouring Noble-man, who underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Husbands injunctions, Laughs, and ſoon teaches her a different and much more pleaſant way of Marriage-life: <hi>Don Pedro</hi> returns, and going to Bed admires his Wives new knowledg; who throwing aſide her Helmet and Breſt-plate, boaſts her having learned a much more eaſie and ſweeter way of Converſing with her Husband.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>Right, and well applied. For the firſt <hi>Inſtructers</hi> of my Infancie was likewiſe called <hi>Peter,</hi> and did Dictate the ſame things difficult and ingrateful: To wit, That <hi>my Adorning ſhould not be that outward Adorning of Plaiting the Hair, and of wearing of Gold,
<note place="margin">1 St. Pet, 3.3.</note> or of putting on of Apparrel:</hi> And declaring
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58998:52"/>me bleſſed, <hi>When I ſuffered many things for Righteouſneſs ſake, and became Partner in the ſufferings of my Spouſe.</hi> But theſe things my latter <hi>Inſtructer</hi> Laught at as Follies and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, he told me, Now were <hi>other times which required other manners:</hi>
                                 <note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> And that I was neither <hi>in Bondage to the old weak and beggarly Elements;</hi> Nor was I ſtill <hi>a Child, which differs nothing from a Servant, but freed and ſet at liberty from the OldYoke.</hi> Whereupon likewiſe he took care leaſt I ſhould too often or too diligently read what former <hi>Inſtructers</hi> had taught, the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Admonitions of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> or the laſt Commands of my Spouſe; Nay, as much as he could he ſtrove to blot out even his Memory, forbidding me the taſting of Wine at our ſolemn Suppers, <hi>in remembrance of him.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>This was indeed, <hi>That he might Eſpouſe you to one Husband and preſent you to him as a chaſte Virgin.</hi>
                                 <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.2.</note> But did you never remember to Admoniſh him of the Treaſon he committed againſt his Lord.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>Yes very often; But he uſed to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that he could not commit any fin, that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58998:52"/>though two do the ſame thing, yet it is not the ſame. That there was another Rule for worldly or ſecular men, <hi>Che non hanno auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita de maneggiar le coſe ſacre,</hi> who have no authority over ſacred things.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>I remember the ſame anſwer lately given to Siſter <hi>Marina,</hi> by Father <hi>Francis. Nel parlatoria delle Monache feneſtra?</hi> But what ſaid thy Siſters and their <hi>Inſtructers</hi> to this, did not they envie this familiarity with thee, and the pleaſure thence to be derived?</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>Oh extreamly, and firſt of all he at <hi>Zybantinum,</hi> who being ſetled in our <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> houſe, had likewiſe purchaſed to himſelf great Authority, but with various Arts, which it would be too long to relate, we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed at length, and that at firſt by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of many Strifes and grievous Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes which ſo Turmoiled, Vexed, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed our <hi>Tutors</hi> (for many of them firſt died) that they had neither the heart to look after our Affairs, nor Power enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain us to our Duty. Nay, ſo far things went that my <hi>Inſtructer</hi> having obtained com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands ſent from the Father, ſought a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Empire over the <hi>Tutors</hi> themſelves, and avouched himſelf to have no leſs Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58998:53"/>then the Father, or the Spouſe given me by the Father.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>Did there riſe no Quarrels from thence?</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>Many indeed. And often truly the Father ſent his Meſſengers to reprove and chaſtiſe the Inſolencie of my Lover; but he either corrupted them with Bribes; or if cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt them he could not, made them guilty of Impoſture and Rebellion, and thereupon by a kind of Law of his own, with cruel Torments removed them out of the way.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>But could theſe things long lie hid?</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>No certainly. I have now received a Meſſage of the coming of my Spouſe, to whom all things are known, and who will Execute ſevere Juſtice: I underſtand from the Relation of our <hi>Pallavicini,</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> his Secretary is already arrived <hi>Incognito,</hi> to make a curious Inquiſition into Mine and my <hi>Inſtructors</hi> manners.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>'Twere beſt then to call for Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in time.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>Alas, many already have been here, who came of their own good-wil, but all in vain, for they could not agree among themſelves what Phyſick to preſcribe; <hi>
                                    <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſinulca</hi> and <hi>Rethulus</hi>'s
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58998:53"/>
                                 <hi>way of Cure by Quick ſilver,</hi> I took; and they preſcribed to add to it <hi>Vomiting</hi> &amp; <hi>Sweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> ſo that what I have a long time received I Vomited and Sweat out. <hi>Sarmeus</hi> and <hi>Crendaſſa,</hi> thought this way too dangerous and violent, and believed a milder Courſe was to be begun, but what, they did not know themſelves; ſome preſcribed one thing, ſome another, <hi>And ſo many men, ſo many minds.</hi> There are thoſe who think if any ſtrong Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy were applied, it might be accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with danger of ſudden death, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are of Opinion to do nothing, but that Colledg of Phyſitians which my <hi>Inſtructer</hi> lately ſummoned in the City of <hi>Mentirdut,</hi> beyond the ſence of all the World, with one Voice pronounced me Pure and of perfect Health; and that an Action of Slander ſhould be decreed againſt all thoſe who durſt report me Infected with the Foul Diſeaſe. Which though I am willing all men ſhould believe; yet I muſt confeſs to thee, I do not my ſelf believe it, for I adjudg the <hi>Venome in my inveterate Fiſtulaes and Ulcers to be ſo knit and bound together with a kind of a dry hardneſs, that though any one ſhould accompany with me, they need not thence fear any mortal contagion.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <pb n="92" facs="tcp:58998:54"/>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>You ſay that only, not to ſcare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your Lovers: But what will your Spouſe ſay, when he knows all theſe things.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>He already knows them, and has already thought of a Divorce, having entred his Action with the Father. What is done in the buſineſs is contained in this Libel, which ſome days ſince <hi>Pallavicini</hi> commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to me; and what ſhall be done, that I am ignorant of, he has promiſed upon his ſoul to let me know with the firſt.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>I will read a little, by your leave. THE INSCRIPTION. <hi>The Eternal Word anſwers to the Father, and ſignifies the Occaſions of his diſguſts with his Spouſe, making inſtance of a Divorce upon theſe accounts.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Sona,</speaker>
                              <p>Take the Libel home with you and read it, but on this condition, that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it to me, and to no one elſe.</p>
                           </sp>
                           <sp>
                              <speaker>Roph.</speaker>
                              <p>I underſtand you, therefore till I return, as much as you can, <hi>Fare-well.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </sp>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="letter">
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:58998:54"/>
            <head>
               <hi>JANUS ALEXANDRUS FERRARI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S OF THE</hi> AUGUSTIN ORDER HIS Sixth Epiſtle, Concerning the Uſefulneſs and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Faith, To the Right Reverend <hi>ADRIAN and PETER of WALLENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Reverend Men,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TIS true indeed you ſay, That Dialogue lately ſent from <hi>Italy;</hi> and which by Letter I Communicated to You, contains a true Image of the <hi>Roman Church.</hi> Who <hi>Uſinulca</hi> is, Boys may learn out of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genis,</hi> who <hi>Rethulus, Sarmens, Crendaſſa,</hi> The tranſpoſition of the Letters ſhows, <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia</hi> is <hi>Rome. Mentirdut, Tridentum</hi> or
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58998:55"/>
               <hi>Trent;</hi> by <hi>Inſtructors</hi> are ſignified <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and by <hi>Tutors, Emperors</hi> and <hi>Kings.</hi> Thus all things are made plain; But what to ſome People ſeems inconvenient, that the ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhould take the rule of their diſcourſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from <hi>Petronius, Aretine, Miletus,</hi> then from holy Scriptures, or graver Hiſtories, that our <hi>Siderius</hi> do's not at all value; For he ſays, That as he believes the minds of holy Men, in their cloſer converſe with God, would be beſt expreſſed in the delicate and lovely <hi>Hebrew</hi> Stile, ſo Minds eſtranged from the <hi>firſt truth,</hi> and alienated from <hi>all goodneſs,</hi> are beſt repreſented in a Scheme of Obſcene and Adulterous Expreſſions. And to that purpoſe he praiſes, in that book which we all account Holy, thoſe Orations of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Cap. XVI. &amp; XXIII. as well as thoſe of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea.</hi> However it ought to be, I altogether leave to you; but I muſt tell you, the Author of this Dialogue is a Heretick, and a moſt implacable Enemy of our Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Wherefore I think we ought to labour more diligently, that our begun demonſtrations may be the ſooner perfected, that ſo the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of the Catholick Faith, may more plainly appear. And to that end, what comes next in order is,</p>
            <div n="7" type="proposition">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:58998:55"/>
               <head>PROPOSITION VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Religion which we call Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, as it was by Christ at firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to his Apoſtles, is in it ſelf, and in the Nature of its Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, moſt unapt for Salvation: Whereupon it was of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for thoſe firſt publiſhers of the Goſpel, enormouſly to wander, and go aſtray from the very Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Catholick Doctrine, and that Scope of the whole Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>EXPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>Tis now about One Thouſand Six Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Sixty ſeven Years, (if we may believe the incertain calculation of a certain <hi>Roman Abbot</hi>) ſince there was in <hi>Judaea,</hi> of Kingly Stock indeed, but very poor Parentage, Born one <hi>Jeſus Sirnamed Chriſt.</hi> He both
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58998:56"/>the Holineſs of His Life, and the Miracles by which He grew Famous, and other Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Doctrine, made Himſelf appear not only to be a Man, but even a Divinity it ſelf. Whence He called Himſelf <hi>Son of the moſt Higheſt, and thought it no Robbery to be Equal with God.</hi> There flouriſhed then in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> World, two moſt powerful kinds of Religion; one of which, was the Worſhip of the <hi>Jews;</hi> the other, that ſo called of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> The firſt preſcribed by the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of all things, and confirmed by many Prodigies, acknowledged but one God; and yet Groaned under ſuch a mighty Load of Ceremonies, that it moved not ſo much the People by the rules of its Governance, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it contained ſo much of the Authority of the Legiſlator. The latter, deviſed only from the Wit of Mankind, as the invention of ſeveral Men are always diverſe, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; contained many things different from, nay, even contrary to the rules of Divine Worſhip; all which notwithſtanding, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in this, That though they taught the Worſhip of many gods, they did not one damn the other; whence that Religion, though compoſed of ſuch manifold variety,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58998:56"/>ſeemed not at all the leſs Simple or United. Therefore both thoſe toilſom rites of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Idolatry of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the moſt Wiſe <hi>Jeſus</hi> quite took away, and reduced all Religion to the firſt Principles of right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Native or ſimple Ingenuity. One only thing he added, and effectually exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Myſtery, the Propitiation and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement of one particular Deity; which by the Sufferings and Death of that Deity was to be perfected. Which Doctrine fetch'd from the moſt ſecret, &amp; holy receſſes of Heaven; and to all paſt Ages of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind utterly unheard of, did moſt wonderfully Illuſtrate, as well the immenſe Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God, as the ſtrict and unaltera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obſervance of Divine Juſtice, whence of neceſſity there muſt needs ariſe and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in minds, at all ſeaſoned with Divine Grace, both an Admiration and Reverence of the Deity, and a veneration of Love, Duty &amp; Gratitude; In which, both the knowledge and uſe of all Religion is conſummated. This <hi>Chriſt</hi> having ſuffered a moſt cruel Death, and again got the Victory over it, being to return to His Fathers place, committed the farther propagation of that Saving Doctrine
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58998:57"/>which he had chiefly Expounded to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Preaching it among all other Nations of the World, to certain of his Kinſmen and Followers, Weak and unlearned Men, and of the meaneſt of the People. Theſe being Born in an obſcure place, bred up among Sordid Fiſher-men, and oppreſſed with Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, having their minds dejected, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of great things, underſtood nothing but what was mean and low, yet they had heard the magnificent promiſes of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, which, being fully perſwaded that he was a Man altogether Divine, they could not at all think Vain, or He in the leaſt a Lyar. Whereupon, when they beheld no way lie open for them to arrive at ampler For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes here, which indeed they had ſenced againſt themſelves by their <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of mind; but that, though they went about under a moſt honourable Embaſſy in the name of God; yet they were every where moſt contumeliouſly treated, and obnoxious to the moſt grievous injuries, they placed their hopes in a future age, dreaming that what for the preſent was denied them, ſhould be enjoyed by them after Death, not unlike to that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58998:57"/>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nuper, Tarpeio quae ſedit culmine, Cornix,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Eſt bene, <hi>non potuit dicere, dixit,</hi> Erit.</l>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A Crow ſitting on the Tarpeian Hill,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Could not cry</hi> all is well, <hi>but cry'd,</hi> it will.</l>
                     </q> And ſeaſoned as it were, by a kind of prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion with this error, they underſtood no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing rightly of all thoſe things they had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther received from ancient Prophecies, or the Promiſes they had heard from their Maſter; for they moſt unſeaſonably and importunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recommended nothing more then Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Forbearance, abſtaining from Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Humility and Moderation of Mind, together with <hi>taking up,</hi> as they called it, <hi>of the Croſs,</hi> and <hi>Crucifying of the Fleſh,</hi> Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial, contempt of the World, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Riches; In a word, the defrauding of Senſe, and renouncing even Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. They urged likewiſe Obedience to Kings and Princes, and that Magiſtracy was not to be ſtrove againſt under any pretence of Religion or holy Orders; but the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Eſtabliſhed by God, to be ſubmitted to; Thus broke they the minds of Men, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58998:58"/>them from all ſtudies after Riches, Honours or Power; and to that end, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they taught of the Glory or Majeſty of the Church, they applied to ſome Spiritual Excellency, and Inward Grace of the Soul; whence it came to paſs, that by all thoſe who are only wiſe for the preſent, they were not only treated with Contempt and Scorn, but perſecuted with Whips and Tortures; and yet even in thoſe things, as in ſome particular good, they uſed to glory.</p>
                  <p>You will perhaps object to them, what St. <hi>Paul</hi> attributes to the <hi>Jews, That there was a Vail drawn over their Hearts</hi> when they read <hi>Moſes,</hi> or any of the Old Prophets, ſo that they could not attain to the Temporal Prerogative, and External Priviledge of the Church, of which they ought to have been the Architects and Governours.</p>
                  <p>Indeed, at the very beginning of his firſt Book, that great Hebrew Prophet has moſt Elegantly writ, <hi>God made two great Lights, the one to rule by Day, and the other to rule by Night.</hi> Which words, do plainly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that the Future dominion of the Church was to be much greater, and more Splendid then the Imperial Majeſtty. For thus
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58998:58"/>writes <hi>Innocent</hi> III. to the Illuſtrious Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of <hi>Conſtantinople. You ought to know,</hi> ſays he,
<note place="margin">c. 6. Solicitae de major: &amp; obed.</note> 
                     <hi>that God made two great Lights in the Firmaments of Heaven, the greater Light to rule by Day, and the leſſer Light to rule by Night; both great, but the one greater. To the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Heaven, that is, the</hi> CATHOLICK CHURCH, <hi>God made two great Lights, that is, inſtituted two Powers; which are the Papal Authority, and Regal Dignity; but that which is to rule by Day, that is, over Spiritual things, is the greater, but that over Carnal the leſs, that there may be known to be as much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Popes and Kings, as there is between Sun and Moon.</hi> The Pope adds, <hi>That though he writ not theſe things as chiding to the Emperour, yet that he might with reaſon chide him.</hi> How much more then are you to be chid O ye A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles? That ſhould have had more Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the explaining Oracles, then any little worldly King or <hi>Byzantine</hi> Prince. As for what the Gloſſary on the Canon Law adds, <hi>Whilſt the Earth is ſeven times bigger then the Moon, and the Sun eight times bigger then the Earth. The Papal Power muſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently be fifty ſeven times bigger then Regal
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58998:59"/>Dignity.</hi> This I ſay, I do not wonder you were ignorant of, nor can I accuſe you for it, ſince in truth, this obſervation could not have been deduced, but out of new and very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular principles, and that by the aſſiſtance of moſt ſubtil Logick, to you unknown.</p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Moſes</hi> ſets forth a moſt exact Image of the Royal Papacy in <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> who did praefigure the Majeſty of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and his Succeſſors; yet St. <hi>Peter</hi> underſtood not a word of this; no nor St. <hi>Paul</hi> neither: For, as for the firſt, that dignity which he ought to have vindicated for himſelf only, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared common to all Chriſtians; and when from thence he ought to have aſſerted his own Authority over the univerſality of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, he collects the quite contrary, to wit, <hi>That the Clergy ought to be ſubject to every Ordinance of Man,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9-14.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the King as Supreme, or to Governours, as being ſent by him.</hi> And the latter in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> has indeed largely and laboriouſly diſcourſed many things, but in a far different ſenſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Prieſthood of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> when he ought to have explained only that one thing; that he and his Succeſſors had <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeck</hi> for their Prototype. As <hi>Campanel de
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58998:59"/>Mon. Hiſp. c.</hi> 5. for he is indeed a High-Prieſt, as of the <hi>Patriarchate of Abraham,</hi> ſo of <hi>the Order of Melchiſedeck, and him God has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a Royal Prieſthood,</hi> and armed him as well with the Civil as Spiritual Sword; for if it were otherwiſe, Chriſt would be a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minutive Law-giver, and not as <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> who was at once both King and Prieſt.</p>
                  <p>And that ſame Ignorance of his, St. <hi>Paul</hi> has elſewhere, as well as in this Epiſtle to the <hi>Rom.</hi> c. ix. more openly betray'd. For when as <hi>Brevengius</hi> witneſſes, <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In auctar Epiſt. obſe. vir.</note> were types of the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and Catholicks; and that the firſt ſignified, that the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> ſhould lead a Life of Poverty and Affliction; but the other, that the <hi>Catholicks</hi> after his Example, ſhould abound in all Riches and Delights. <hi>Paul</hi> omitting all thoſe things, which only made to this purpoſe, explains both Stories of Mans Eternal Damnation and Salvation, which he ſhould obtain after the putting off Mortality; which error is the more inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable, becauſe he might eaſily have learnt from the ſalutation of <hi>Gabriel</hi> to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> (which doubtleſs was ſometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58998:60"/>in thoſe days) <hi>That our Pope was to Reign over the Houſe of Jacob for ever;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 1.33.</note> that is, both he, and all the Clergy following him, ſhall live Plentifully and Splendidly in this World, as moſt ſubtilly he again divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whom we have before praiſed.</p>
                  <q>—<hi>Lymphata mente Sacerdos.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>—<hi>Frantick or Phantaſtical Prieſt.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>But with the ſame, moſt manifeſt error do's St <hi>Paul</hi> wreſt that Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the Eighth <hi>Pſalm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. XV. Heb. 11.</note> to Chriſt alone: <hi>God ſhall put all things under his Feet;</hi> When by that is clearly meant <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and their Succeſſors in the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> To wit, <hi>To them God ſhall ſubject the Sheep, that is, the Chriſtians; the Bulls, that is, the Jews and Hereticks; the Beaſts of the Field, that is,</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingius <hi>and the Pagans; the Fiſhes of the Sea, that is, the Souls in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory;
<note place="margin">Summa Theol. Part. 3. c. 5.</note> and the Fowls of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that is, the Bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and Angels;</hi> as, full of Enthuſiaſm, the <hi>moſt ſpiritual Antoninus</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains it.</p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:58998:60"/>
                  <p>But it exceeds all manner of wonder, that theſe unlearned Apoſtles ſhould not lay hold upon thoſe things which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſo diligently inculcated concerning the Power and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> under him. That unleſs any one with that late Arch Heretick <hi>Cocceius;</hi> will tranſpoſe every thing into a Spiritual ſenſe, he will be forced to confeſs, that it cannot be otherwiſe explained, then as the moſt Noble Count of <hi>Claraval,</hi> not ſo lately has done it.
<note place="margin">Scioppius in eo ad nobil. Germ de ſolendo re &amp; div. Eccl. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golſt. 40. 1605.</note> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to whoſe interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>the Gentiles walked,</hi> ſays the Prophet, ſpeaking of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, <hi>They walked in thy Light, and Kings in the Brightneſs of thy Riſing. Then ſhalt thou ſee and wonder, and rejoyce when the riches of the Sea, and all the ſubſtance of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhall come unto thee. The Sons of ſtrangers ſhall build thy Temples, and their Kings ſhall miniſter unto thee. Thy Gates ſhall be open day and night, that they may bring unto thee the Riches of all Nations, and their Kings ſhall be brought. Whatever Kingdom will not ſerve thee ſhall Periſh. The Emperours of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58998:61"/>that oppreſſed thee, ſhall adore the footſteps of thy Succeſſors. I will place thee in the Pride of Generations, that is, (in Secular Pomp and Splendor) and thou ſhalt ſuck the Milk of the Gentiles,</hi> (Chald. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſatiate thy ſelf with the riches of the People) and thou ſhalt ſuck the breſts of Kings,</hi> (LXX. Interpret. <hi>Thou ſhalt devour the riches of Kings.) For Braſs I will bring Gold, and for Iron Silver, and for Wood Braſs, and for Stones Iron.</hi> So he upon the LX. Chapter; which words,
<note place="margin">Apoc. XXI.</note> though made ſo clear by our Interpreter, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt St. <hi>John</hi> renders ambiguous, nay, delivers in a quite different ſenſe, and but ill apply'd to the Church Triumphant; who as he there out of a certain innate <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>Puſilanimity,</hi> deſcribes the Angel refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the honours offered him, ſo without doubt would neither have accepted this, nor that which of the mighty honours to be done to his Colleague St. <hi>Peter,</hi> is elſewhere foretold by <hi>Eſaiah,</hi> to wit, <hi>Kings and Queens, ſhall prostrate on the Earth adore thee, and lick the duſt of thy Feet.</hi> Which indeed, not in <hi>Peter,</hi> as uncapable of thoſe honours, yet in his Succeſſors we ſee happily compleated.</p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:58998:61"/>
                  <p>But yet theſe dull Fiſhermen, if they had but a little regarded their own proper Trade, might have eaſily underſtood what fortunes they were to have fiſh'd out for themſelves. For can there be any thing plainer then what they may read in <hi>Habakkuk. And makeſt men as Fiſhes of the Sea,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 1. <hi>v.</hi> 14, &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>as the creeping things that have no ruler over them. They take up all of them with the Angle, they catch them in their Net, and gather them in their Drag. Therefore they rejoyce and are glad. Therefore they Sacrifice unto their Net, and burn Incenſe unto their Drag; becauſe by them their Portion is Fat, and their Meat Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi> But that by this Fiſhing with the Hook, is to be underſtood the Preaching of the Goſpel, is as well taught by that Parable, they received from the mouth of Chriſt, as by the promiſe made to St. <hi>Peter, I will make thee a Fiſher of Men:</hi> That is, as <hi>Reginald Pool</hi> interprets it, <hi>Thou and thy Succeſſors ſhall have dominion over all Men, ruling over Kings, and commanding, regulating, and caſting out Emperours.</hi> But Chriſt gave not only the fiſhing of Men, but likewiſe the Fiſhing for Money, and ſo eaſily purchaſed to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58998:62"/>a right of Fiſhing in all Secular Ponds. <hi>The Kings of the Earth</hi> (ſays he to <hi>Peter) from whom do they receive Tribute? Not certainly from us, for we are Children and therefore free: But go thou to the Sea and caſt forth a Hook, and take up the firſt Fiſh that cometh up.
<q>Tros Rutuluſve fuat nullo diſcrimine habetor.</q>
                        <q>
                           <hi>No matter of what Kingdom, Country, or Nation.</hi>
                        </q> That take, and when thou haſt opened his mouth thou ſhalt find a piece of Money, that take.</hi> Certainly,
<q>
                        <hi>Niſi tunc Petri mens Laeva fuiſſit.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Vnleſs Peter were then Light-headed.</hi>
                     </q> He could not but from thoſe words gather what a great Fiſhing-right was Eſtabliſhed in him; but though he had ſometimes the mannagement of fiercer minds, yet it muſt be confeſſed that he being of a more fearful temper, was very inſufficient for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:58998:62"/>taking or ſupporting any great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> v.</note> for if fear ſeized him and all his Conſorts, when in the Lake <hi>Geneza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,</hi> they once took ſome few Fiſhes more then ordinary, with how great a trembling would they have been ſurprized to have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held their Nets infolding mighty Whales, and the live Bodies of men: From which fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, I likewiſe believe it happened that when <hi>All manner of four footed Beaſts, and wild Beaſts, and Creeping things, and Fowls of the Air were ſent down to him in a certain ſheet, and he was</hi> twice <hi>or thrice commanded that he ſhould kill and eat;</hi> yet he doubted and durſt not touch, <hi>whereupon the Veſſel was again taken up into Heaven:</hi> And yet 'tis evident accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Interpretation of the moſt Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Baronius.</hi> God by this Viſion as by ſome ſolemn Inveſtiture, would confer upon <hi>Peter</hi> the power of Slaughtering men at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; yet he, that propriety of Supreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, out of his Fiſherman-ſimplicity then ſo neglected, that it was in danger of having ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly come to nought, had it not been recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by his Succeſſors, and among others aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Paul,</hi> not that Idiot of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> but <hi>Paul</hi> the V. though indeed ſomething unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58998:63"/>and ſo not altogether unhappily. <hi>Peter</hi> therefore applied himſelf to (I know not what) Spiritual Fiſhing, hunting after myſtical Fiſhes, and incloſing them in the Net of ſome inviſible Kingdom in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, when he ought to have exerciſed his Fiſhing-trade in the Waters, and thoſe the largeſt and deepeſt: For, <hi>In great Waters, great Fiſhes are to be taken;</hi> as it is in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, Now the Waters <hi>are People, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Tongues, and Languages.</hi> Wherefore Chriſt likewiſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him <hi>to launch out in the deep,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>and let down their Nets for a draught:</hi> That is, <hi>Go up to</hi> Rome <hi>which had a vaſt Dominion over all People,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Serm. 2. in Feſt. Petr.</note> 
                     <hi>and from whence they might ſpread their Nets over all the World to catch all Nations.</hi> As is well obſerved by <hi>Pope In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> III.</p>
                  <p>But if any one ſhould ſay, thoſe Antient Oracles and Promiſes of Chriſt you have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſo much praiſed, were not delivered in naked and ſimple, but in figurative words, ſo that they could not be ſo accurately under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the Apoſtles: Let him conſider <hi>Peters</hi> own ſaying, <hi>Here are two Swords;</hi> and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58998:63"/>Chriſts Anſwer, <hi>It is enough.</hi> And then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain his Command, <hi>Put up thy Sword into its ſheath:</hi> What can more clear and plainly be ſaid, to aſſert the Spiritual as well as the Civil Sword, to be given to Eccleſiaſtical Princes? For had the Civil Sword not at all appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Peter,</hi> certainly Chriſt when mention was made of two Swords, ought to have ſaid <hi>It is too much;</hi> but he only ſaid, <hi>It is enough.</hi> Nor had he commanded <hi>Peter, Put up</hi> thy <hi>Sword into the ſheath.</hi> If that Sword had not belonged to <hi>Peter,</hi> as is moſt diſcreetly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by <hi>Boniface</hi> VIII. <hi>in Extravagantibus:</hi> Where the Comment teaches the diſtinction between <hi>the Sword out of the ſheath, and the Sword in the ſheath: That being viſible, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Material, and by couſequence Temporal; this inviſible, and therefore Spiritual, yet both belonging to Peter:</hi> For if the Sword in the ſheath be mine, certainly the ſame will be mine when it ſhall be out of the ſheath. Yet notwithſtanding all this the Apoſtles collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from hence things quite different, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading themſelves that the Uſe of the Temporal Sword was prohibited them by their Maſter. So hard a thing it is to be wiſe, when the mind is once ſeaſoned with Erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Principles.</p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:58998:64"/>
                  <p>However I muſt confeſs ſome of them have ſometimes pitcht upon better things, and converted their thoughts to more ſublime Matters; as when the Mother of the <hi>Zebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees</hi> with her Sons, requeſted a certain place to be aſſigned them, to wit, next on the Right and Left-hand of Chriſt: And again, when the Apoſtles contended among themſelves for Precedency, and made Enquiry who ſhould be the greateſt. I confeſs likewiſe, that Chriſt anſwered very ſharply to theſe Requeſts, and reproving their Ambition, <hi>You know,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 20.</note> ſaid he, <hi>that the Princes of the Gentiles exerciſed Dominion over them, and they that are great exerciſe Authority upon them; but it ſhall not be ſo among you, but whoſoever will be great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, let him be your Miniſter.</hi> And again, <hi>He that would be the greateſt among you, let him be as the leaſt; and he that would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as him that ſerveth.</hi> Which words might poſſibly diſturb them, and lead them into that Error, as if it were forbid them to affect Government, or ſeek Empire over Emperours; but however that were; In this at leaſt the Apoſtles grievouſly err'd, that they gave the ſame Precepts to their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:58998:64"/>which had been given to them, when the Reaſon of things are quite otherwiſe: For as <hi>Severinus</hi> of <hi>Mozambane,</hi> has moſt right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved in his <hi>Golden Commentary</hi> to his Brother <hi>Laelius: Poſtquam recen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorum Portuna ſacerdotum,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De Statu. Im. Gem. cap. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne quantum a tenuibus Antiquiſ-ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum rebus diſceſſit; Abſurdum fuerit illosamplius adſtringere velle Obſoletis, ſuper modeſtia ejus Ordinis hominum a ſalvatore promulgatis. Et fortaſſe iſtae leges ad prima illa tempora duntaxat debebant valere; Nam id revera ridiculum erat, homines Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores aut Textores Primum locum affectare, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in diem victus aut labore manuum aut ſtipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus collatis quaerebatur.</hi>
                     <q>Since the fortunes of the latter Clergy has been ſo wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly changed even from the ſlighteſt things of the Ancient, it would be abſurd any longer to tie up them to thoſe obſolete Laws, for the Modeſty ſake of that firſt Order of men to whom they were at firſt publiſhed by our Saviour, and poſſibly thoſe Laws were deſigned only to be of force in thoſe firſt Times. For it would certainly have been very Ridiculous that Fiſhermen and Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſhould have affected the firſt places,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58998:65"/>who were daily to ſeek their Bread, either from the Labour of their hands, or Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wages.</q> Which diſtinction the Apoſtles not obſerving, gave occaſion to Hereticks, and to thoſe who are often worſe then Hereticks, <hi>Politicians;</hi> to think that thoſe Anſwers of our Saviours might appertain likewiſe to our Days, then which no Opinion can be more pernicious to our Church, or more ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to Pious minds. And hence it comes to paſs, that the Right of Fiſhing which in all Lands, nay, even in the Super-caeleſtial and Infernal Waters, does <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to our <hi>Popes,</hi> is at this day Prohibited them, and that neither in the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Ocean, the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea, the Lake <hi>Lemane,</hi> nor the Rivers of <hi>Germany,</hi> they are admitted ſuch free Fiſhing as formerly. Nay, it was once to be feared leaſt it would have been Prohibited in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Adriatick,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epiſt. Piſcat venet ad Paulum</hi> V.</note> as one of his own Tribe, <hi>Piſanius di Piz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zoni,</hi> an Honeſt man, and a Lover of his Country, very Brotherly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhes. So much is that Puzillaminity of the Apoſtles; and that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>Simplicity,</hi> in which they uſed to Glory, hurtful to the preſent Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="demonstration">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:58998:65"/>
                  <head>DEMONSTRATION.</head>
                  <p>Since the Apoſtles aim'd at nothing High, nothing Sublime, but with broken and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected minds, praiſed and recommended only Plebeian Virtues, ſuch as Modeſty, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Humility, by which not only the Churches Welfare is impeded, but the whole Structure utterly overturned: It is of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conſequence, that they Enormouſly have ſtraied from the foundation of the Catholick Doctrine, and the whole Scope of that Faith; and therefore the Religion by them delivered is in it ſelf, and the Nature of its Principles very unapt for the attaining of Salvation, which is what was to be Demonſtrated.</p>
                  <p>It will be therefore our Buſineſs quite to remove, or at leaſt to amend all ill placed things from thoſe Principles, and accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date them to the Eſtabliſhment of the Sacred Empire; which in our next Letters we ſhall begin to do. In the mean time, Farewel, and take diligent care of <hi>Brevingius</hi> Health, <hi>Paris</hi> Cal. <hi>June,</hi> MDCLxvii.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="letter">
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:58998:66"/>
            <head>
               <hi>JANUS ALEXANDRUS FERRARIUS OF THE</hi> AUGUSTIN ORDER. HIS Seventh Epiſtle Concerning the Uſefulneſs and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Faith. To the Right Reverend <hi>ADRIAN and PETER of WALENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reverend Brothers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> as it was at firſt dictated by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> is both in <hi>its ſelf,</hi> and in the <hi>Nature</hi> of its Principles, not at all fit or proper for <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Salvation,</hi> or eſtabliſhing the <hi>Royal Prieſthood</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> We have in the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Epiſtle at large ſet forth. There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains that we as evidently demonſtrate what
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58998:66"/>is therefore to be done with it; To which end we lay down,</p>
            <div n="8" type="proposition">
               <head>PROPOSITION VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though the Chriſtian Religion do's unreaſonably, and even to abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, differ from the ends and aim of our holy Roman Church; yet it is not at all adviſeable, that where it is approved by Reaſon, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced by Cuſtom, and establiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Authority of Princes, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſhould be made openly to ruine it at one violent &amp; impetuous ſtroke.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>EXPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. There have been thoſe indeed who have adjudged it ought utterly to be overthrown, and openly deſtroyed; as alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo erroneous from the moſt <hi>profitable,</hi> and therefore main end of <hi>True Faith:</hi> That
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58998:67"/>there ſeemed but little hopes it ſhould ever by any Art or Induſtry be wrought to our purpoſe; or if (poſſibly) it were never ſo well accomodated, there was ſtill ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, leſt at ſome time or other it ſhould una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares revert to its <hi>priſtine</hi> Nature, and to that <hi>dull</hi> and <hi>Sterril genius</hi> firſt poſſeſt it. And that this was no vain fear, the experience of former, as well as preſent times, has taught us. For from whence have the <hi>Rebel Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> raiſed more, and more <hi>ſerviceable</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to aſſail the Powers of our <hi>Sacred Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> then from the moſt <hi>hidden</hi> and <hi>ſecret</hi> Myſteries of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion?</hi> Which if they had been not only <hi>hidden,</hi> and as it were <hi>Plaiſtred</hi> over, but utterly blotted out, they could never have provided themſelves of ſuch vaſt quantity of Arms againſt our <hi>Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. But though this may have <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently</hi> enough been thought of by ſome; yet before we can <hi>aſſent</hi> to it, we think it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient other ways of proceeding be firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined; For in affairs of this kind, which are on every ſide encompaſſed with difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the firſt way preſenting it ſelf, is not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately to be held, but all are to be made
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58998:67"/>trial of, that after having diligently compared one with another, we may make choice of the ſafeſt and eaſieſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. And the firſt thing herein to be taken notice of, is, what has in this caſe been the opinion of wiſe Men in former times. Among which, we may account of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> a Man, as the event teſtifies, of a very clear Judgment; whoſe example we ſhould be the more earneſt to imitate, becauſe he ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proſecuted the ſame purpoſe, and was verſt in the ſame cauſe with us. Wherefore the very Hereticks themſelves make him a <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>league</hi> with our <hi>Pope;</hi> and whilſt they will have <hi>Antichriſt</hi> to be two-headed, or at leaſt two-horned, they give the right Horn to <hi>our moſt holy Father;</hi> and the Left they place on <hi>Mahomet,</hi> For this <hi>Mahomet,</hi> when out of his quickneſs of Spirit, he perceived how much the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> was averſe to his purpoſe, as diverting Men from ſeeking after preſent Felicity, and ſoftning and depreſſing their minds with the awe and reverence of Weak and Unwarlike Virtues, recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peace inſtead of War, Gentleneſs inſtead of Fierceneſs, Service inſtead of Freedom, and Prayers and Tears inſtead of Arms;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58998:68"/>though he believed it utterly pernicious and averſe to his deſign; yet he judged it was not to be demoliſhed at a Blow, or by open Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence overthrown; And therefore among other Chapters of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> he wiſely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his People, <hi>That they ſhould believe for truth thoſe books ſent amongſt them of the Prophets and Apostles, and ſhould therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt the Son of Mary, to be the Spirit of God, and an Apoſtle ſent by him, and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and Moſaical Law he every where approves.</hi> Nay, on theſe very Foundations he ſeems to lay the Superſtructure of his whole Doctrine, ſupporting it by the authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; Whereupon the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> with a ſubtilty like ours, in relation to the Pope, find mention made of their Prophet, in both books of Old and New Teſtament. For in the Law, <hi>Deut. XXXIII. v.</hi> 2. where it is ſaid, <hi>The Lord came from Sinai, and roſe up from Seir unto them, and ſhined forth from Mount Paran.</hi> Thoſe words they will have diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſignifie that the Law deſcended to <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Goſpel to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and the Alcoran to <hi>Mahomet.</hi> And as that Prophet <hi>Abulkaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Surata</hi> Lxxi teſtifies, <hi>Jeſus the Son of Mary ſaid, O Children of Iſrael, I am the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58998:68"/>of God to you, that I may verifie the Law you have, and announce a Prophet to come after me, whoſe name ſhall be Achimed.</hi> That is, as <hi>Beidavins</hi> interprets it, <hi>Mahomet;</hi> which likewiſe a certain <hi>Saracen</hi> Dialogiſt in <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Abucara,</hi> very wittily aſſerts to have once been writ in the book of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, when he ſays to the Chriſtian, <hi>In the Goſpel Chriſt writ ſaying, I ſend to you a Prophet called Mahomet.</hi> To which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, <hi>But the Goſpel contains no memory of it;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Opuſc. 19. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Opuſc. xiv. edita a. G.</note> The Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barian replies. <hi>It anciently indeed contained it, but you have blotted it out.</hi> Subtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arguing it from the xiv. chap. of St. <hi>John,</hi> which diſcourſes of the <hi>Comforter;</hi> Where on the other ſide the page, in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, I am perſwaded might be extant alſo the prophecy of the Occidental <hi>Comforter,</hi> which is reſident in the Cabinet of the <hi>Popes</hi> breſt; But if that is not to be found in any of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies or Tranſlations now adays, 'tis done by the cunning of the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and certain kind of <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> whom I would ſwear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſixteen hundred years ago, had with ſpecial care blotted all thoſe things out of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58998:69"/>Scripture. But for theſe reaſons the <hi>Turks,</hi> if at this day offered a book of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, tranſlared into <hi>Arabick,</hi> receive it with an exceſs of reverence, and moſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly kiſs it, as a Book ſent down from Heaven; and in which of Old, mention was made of their Prophet. From all which we may gather that great Architect, as well of a new Principality, as a new Religion, judged ſome outward ſhow, and external Scheme of the Chriſtian Religion was to be ſet forth; whilſt its internal Power and Force was utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extinct. To which purpoſe, though he often ſpoke Magnificently of the Scriptures, yet he utterly forbid the Reading, or nice diſputing about, or ſearch into them, content with this as <hi>Achimed Iben Edris</hi> ingeniouſly elſewhere profeſſes, that he made them ſerve to his purpoſe; and for this reaſon he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged them with a ſupplimental <hi>Alcoran,</hi> which as the laſt dictates of the Prophetick Spirit, contained the perfect principles of Salvation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. The courſes of this moſt happy Monarch, and with our Pope, <hi>Joint Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>league and Brother in Antichriſt,</hi> why ſhould not we follow? For if he only to erect a groſs
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58998:69"/>and corporeal Empire, believed the uſe of ſuch exquiſite Arts ſo neceſſary, of how much more ſubtile induſtry ſhall we ſtand in need to raiſe up our Myſtical and Spiritual King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; leaſt it chance to offend any Eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its Foundations be ſolidly laid, and the whole machine ſo firmly compact &amp; brought to that height, that it become the terror of its Enviers, and be able to ſupport its ſelf by its own ſtrength. For as ſuch an Empire ought to be compoſed of a mixture of Divine and Humane things, that it may be <hi>Spiritually-corporeal,</hi> and <hi>Inviſibly-viſible,</hi> ſo it is of neceſſity that the Arts whereby 'tis erected, ſhould agree to both thoſe kinds. Thus profane things with Sacred, Truth with Falſhood, Heaven with Earth, are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily mixed: Thus Churches will at the ſame time be Fortreſſes, Monaſteries, Caſtles, Iſlands fitted into the figures of Crowns; and the Croſier or Paſtoral Crook, be at once both a Murderers Club, and a Regal Scepter; But he who ſhall employ all theſe Arts to the eſtabliſhing of Sacred Empire, will every way appear a true <hi>Leviathan,</hi> much ſtronger, and more formidable then <hi>Hobbs his Leviathan;</hi> Then which what can be invented, at once
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58998:70"/>more ſlender and more ſtrong.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. Therefore let not any fear of thoſe Arms the Hereticks may fetch from Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Doctrine diſturb us; For the ſame things were to be feared by the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> even from very Subtile Hereticks. For it may always happen, that Chriſtian Religion boyling like a kind of Fermentation, may ſeparate it ſelf from oppoſing and Heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Doctrines; and caſting them off, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert its ſelf to its priſtine Purity, and liquid Simplicity; which yet has not happened in many Ages, whilſt <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> mixt with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometiſm</hi> do's at this day remain in the ſame, <hi>feculent craſis,</hi> or filthy temperature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. Moreover, if this affright us, or we ſuffer our ſelves to be ſcared by unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable fears, we ſhall never reap any bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit from the errors of others. For ſince Falſhood without a mixture of Truth, nor Evil without a Foundation of Goodneſs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubſiſt; It will be always to be doubted, leaſt Truth and Goodneſs ſhould withdraw themſelves from Falſhood and Evil, and leave them.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:58998:70"/>
                     <hi>Veluti Nudos in littore piſces</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>— <hi>Like Naked Fiſhes on the Share.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>The conſequence of which over provident fear would be, that only pure truth, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compounded goodneſs were to be followed and taught to others, whereby all the fruit and advantage might accrue to us by Falſhood, and Evil would Periſh and be loſt.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Certainly,
<q>
                        <hi>Nil prodeſt quod non laedere poſſit idem.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <hi>There's nothing profitable, but may likewiſe hurt.</hi>
                     </q> So let us <hi>deſpiſe Food,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Fab. Inſtir. cr l. 2. c. 26.</note> 
                     <hi>becauſe it is ſometimes the cauſe of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper. Let us never go into a Houſe, becauſe they ſometimes fall on the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants Heads: Who is ignorant that Fire and Water, without which ther's no living; and not to ſtay, at Earthly things, the Sun and Moon, thoſe Sovereign Lights, are ſometimes Noxious and Hurtful?</hi> The diſpute therefore lies not, whether from thoſe reliques of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:58998:71"/>Religion any great damage may accrue to us; but whether more good be to be hoped thence, or evil to be feared. But we have already from the example of the moſt crafty <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and evident reaſon ſhewed, That if we ſhould utterly renounce all Chriſtianity, there would no ſolid Foundation remain, whereon to erect our Machines.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. To theſe fall pat both the Judgment and Example of that great Man, and moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Artiſt in framing of Religions <hi>Gulielmus Poſtellus,</hi> S. R. E. <hi>Presbyter,</hi> &amp; who in the latter age, having Travelled through almoſt the whole World, was at length, being an old Man of above an hundred, ſetled by royal Bounty at <hi>Paris,</hi> in the Monaſtery of St. <hi>Martins</hi> in the Fields. This Man, even in the midſt of <hi>Paris,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verdier, Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Proſopog. des ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines Illuſtres.</hi>
                     </note> both publickly taught &amp; delivered in writing, that a certain Woman, his Familiar, whom he called <hi>Mother Jone,</hi> was the Saviour of Woman-kind, with the ſame right that Chriſt was of the Males. Who would believe, that in the Capital City of ſo renowned and flouriſhing a Kingdom; in the midſt of ſuch light of all Knowledge,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:58998:71"/>and Doctrine; among ſuch crouds of wiſe and learned Men, any one ſhould dare to expoſe ſuch ſhameful and prodigious trifles, unleſs he had conjoyn'd them with the true Hiſtory of <hi>Chriſt?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apolog. pro Herod. Henr. Steph. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note> And when to his Friends and to <hi>Stephanus,</hi> who relates this to us, he at <hi>Venice</hi> once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion diſliked him; yet that it was not to be quite caſt off, but tempered with the <hi>Turkiſh,</hi> and the <hi>Jewiſh:</hi> What elſe could he mean, but that Chriſt was not with violent hands to be deſtroyed, but with a kind of friendly embrace to be ſtifled?</p>
                  <p n="9">9. And the long experience of former times, commends likewiſe this way of acting; and thence ſprung that Oracle of the moſt holy Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> who inſtigated by the Spirit of Satan, and raviſh'd at the ſight of that vaſt Maſs of Treaſure he ſaw gathered by Indulgencies. <hi>Hem quantum,</hi> inquit, <hi>nobis Profuit iſta fabula de Chriſto. How much,</hi> ſays he, <hi>has this fable of Chriſt gain'd us?</hi> So the Image of Chriſtianity, may every way be profitable to our affairs; provided we know how to make good uſe of it: But that
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:58998:72"/>depends ſolely on the dexterity and induſtry of thoſe concerned, for Religion is,
<q>
                        <l>— <hi>Come il Coltel,
<note place="margin">Il Paſtor Fido. Act. 1. Sce. 4.</note> cheſi tu'l prendi</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In quelle parte ove per'l uſo humano,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>La man ſadatta, a chi l'adopra e buono</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ma ch'il prende one fere, e ſpeſſo morte.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus Engliſhed by the excellent <hi>Fanſhaw.</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>As Knives which if they warily be caught</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>By that ſafe part, which for the hand was wrought</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Are uſeful, but if raſhly they be t'ane</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>By'th Edge or Point one may be Hurt or Slain.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> So the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, if we lay hold on that part which preſents it in its naked Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and truth, we Periſh; if otherwiſe, it ſerves excellently to our profit and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: For ſo is that truly fulfill'd which the bleſſed <hi>Campanella</hi> has ſaid, <hi>That opinion, which almoſt all People conceive and believe of the Chriſtian Religion, do's very much avail:</hi> Make them but therefore believe, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever appertains to our Pope, the ſame all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertains to Chriſt; and that at whatever of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends the one, the other will likewiſe be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:58998:72"/>Do not you eaſily ſee that with ſo much the more Pomp and Glory the name of Chriſt is expoſed, ſo much the more is the Power and Authority of our Pope amplified?</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Hiſtorians relate of the <hi>Templars,</hi> that they were condemned to exquiſite puniſhments,
<note place="margin">Du Puys dans l' Hiſtoire des Templaires.</note> for that they openly renounced <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and determin'd the rooting out of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith; and yet the cleareſt Writers teſtifie their Innocency of theſe Crimes. So <hi>Maze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> lately,
<note place="margin">Dans l' Hiſtoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re de <hi>France.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Il' n'y a point d' homme de bon ſens qui croye que tou't l'ordre ait eſte cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable des enormites qu' on lay impoſoit. There is no Man of ſound ſenſe, who believes the whole order guilty of thoſe Enormities wherewith they are charged.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon many think they were guilty of no other Crime, but only the not religiouſly enough obſerving the Papal Majeſty. <hi>Quelques ans diſent qu' ils n' eſtorent pas ſi impiet ni ſi mechans qu' on les fuiſoit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gerard du Hail del Eſtat de <hi>France</hi> liv. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>mais qu'il Eſtoient riches,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Some ſay, they were
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:58998:73"/>not ſo Impious, nor ſo Wicked, as they were made; but that they were Rich, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> they ſpoke too freely and publickly of the Vices Cheats and Impoſtures of the Roman See, and againſt the debauches of the Eccleſiaſticks,</hi> are the words of another <hi>French</hi> writer. But though theſe things were ſo, they do not a whit clear them to any one who believes the cauſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the cauſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> See, to be the ſame; for unleſs that be firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allowed, I confeſs I ſhould hardly be convinced how they could be ſo unmercifully perſecuted without the Infamy of extream Envy, and horrid Cruelty. But if thoſe who ſcoff at the <hi>Pope,</hi> are believed to make a Mock of the Eternal Deity of <hi>Chriſt, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> is not to be thought unmerciful, though he cruciated them with moſt dreadful Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and cauſed them to be Burnt in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piatory Flames; Nor ought it to trouble us, nor raiſe in us any ill ſuſpition, That when <hi>Molaeus,</hi> the chief of that Order, cited the <hi>Pope</hi> to appear within fourty days at the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he ſhould on the very day depart this Life. For it is not credible that the <hi>Pope</hi> would appear only at the Citation of that Man; or if at that fatal term appointed
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:58998:73"/>he would appear, and willingly ſubmit his Majeſty to the Judgment of Chriſt, by that he ſhewed he had little diſtruſt of his Affairs, as if Chriſt were eaſily to be perſwaded that in Burning the Templars, he acted for the Common good; indeed theſe things are not eaſily diſtinguiſhed.
<q>Le temporel S'allie ſi ſubtile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment avec le ſpirituel et del intereſt del homme on ſait faire ſi adroitement la cauſe de Dieu,
<note place="margin">Dans la preface au Card Rachlieu ſur ſon livre del immortallitat del ame.</note> &amp; il ſurvient des occaſions ſi melees de ces choſes, qu'ill eſt malaiſe faire la ſeparation.</q> 
                     <hi>Temporal things are ſo ſubtilly allyed to ſpirituals, and the Intereſt of man is ſo artificially made the cauſe of God, and ſuch mixt occaſions happen in theſe matters, that it is hard to make any ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:</hi> As our <hi>Silhonius</hi> lately very well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed. But I muſt believe that Chriſt though very little vers'd in <hi>Suarez Metaphyſicks,</hi> or <hi>Caſtanaeus</hi> his <hi>Diſtinctions,</hi> eaſily found out the difference.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. But let us grant that there may danger accrue, by even the leaſt remains of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Apoſtolick Faith, yet from thence it does not follow that they are utterly to be Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:58998:74"/>unleſs the ſucceſs of the deſign ſeem apparent to us; for 'tis prudence not only to inſpect what may be uſeful and profitable to us, but in the firſt place what may do it: For 'twere fooliſh to make an attempt, where the very condition of things is oppoſite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Where therefore the Chriſtian Religion by the Sublimity of its Principles, the Sanctity of its Precpets, the Majeſty of its Miracles, the Efficacy of its Doctrine, and other ſigns of its Divinity has inſinuated into the minds of men, where by long Cuſtome and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Traditions of Parents and Elders, and by Laws of Princes it is Confirmed, ſo that the Name of JESUS is Worſhipped with a Divine Trembling and Adoration, and an Horrour conceived againſt all thoughts of Blaſpheming it. Do not you perceive, <hi>moſt Reverend Brothers,</hi> how raſh an attempt it would there be, how bold, how full of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, how dubious of any proſperous Succeſs, to undertake the overthrow of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by open Violence and one ſuddain Blow?</p>
                  <p n="12">12. But where things are more at Liberty, and that Old Doctrine of the Apoſtles not ſo firmly ſeated in the minds of men; there
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58998:74"/>I muſt confeſs to Act with full Sail, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and without doubts, or ambages to Preach a new Goſpel, and better fitted to our Advantage, both may done and ought. Which ſafe way being by the firſt <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Apoſtles ſent into <hi>America,</hi> of old neglected; our Sacred Empire, ſuffered thereby no ſmall damage, as the bleſſed, and already by us often praiſed <hi>Campanella,</hi> rightly argues; who leaſt hereafter we ſhould fall into the ſame Errors, Elegantly bound up all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Inſtitutions as well in a brief <hi>Summary</hi> of the Law, as in a new <hi>Catechiſtical Method:</hi> A <hi>Summary,</hi> to wit, on which the Law and the Prophets all depend, contained in theſe Conceptions. <hi>There is not ſo much Reverence to be uſed to it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De Monar. Hiſpan. in Apend.</note> 
                     <hi>among that people who never before heard of the Name of Chriſt, as to the name of the Pope, that they may the more firmly adhere to our Religion, and that it become neceſſary that they ſeek to us, both for the Moral Rules of Life, and the way of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Eternal Salvation.</hi> But the Method of the <hi>Myſtagogy,</hi> or firſt draught of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm,</hi> though it be a little more Prolix, yet by reaſon of its ſingular Elegancy, I cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:58998:75"/>Tranſcribing it, not doubting but you likewiſe, <hi>moſt Reverend Brothers,</hi> though you have often elſe-where Read it, will take ſome pleaſure in once more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewing it.
<note place="margin">De Mon. Hiſ. c. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>Opertet inquit docere miſſos a Deo fuiſſi Magiſtros, veluti Moyſen &amp; alios, quibus cum Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus parum fidei haberet, Deum ipſe aſſumſiſſe carnem humanam, flagrantique noſtro amore,</hi> &amp;c.
<q>It is convenient, <hi>ſays he,</hi> to teach
<note n="*" place="margin">Meaning the Indians in America.</note> them, that there were Maſters ſent from God, to whom then the World gave little Faith; God himſelf aſſumed Humane fleſh, and Burning with Love towards us, took upon him our Nature, that he might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as an Inſtrument to teach us, by what ways we were to reach Heaven, and how Truth was to be practiſed; and this only by Friendly perſwaſions, not by force of Arms: Moreover that God himſelf did by his own Example, Ratifie and Seal what he Taught; thereby Demonſtrating how we were to lead our Converſations here upon Earth, and leaſt after he had Taught us, we by any terrors of Death ſhould fall away
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:58998:75"/>from God, and his Divine Worſhip; he firſt ſubmitted himſelf to Death, being ſlain by cruel Tyrants, that we might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Foot-ſteps; and that on the third day Riſing again from the Dead, he aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Heaven, leaving his Vicar upon Earth, who is called the <hi>Pope,</hi> who ſits in his Tribunal, filled full of Heavenly Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, with many mighty Princes, Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Divine Truth, among whom the King of <hi>Spain</hi> is the chief. Laſtly, that God moved with Mercy towards them when they were Idolaters, ſent their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to reduce them into the way of Truth, and by the <hi>Pope</hi> and King of <hi>Spain</hi> (from whoſe World they are divided by a vaſt Ocean) draw them to himſelf. That to this end our knowledg in building Ships was enlarged, our Art in Navigation increaſed, and our skill in taming Horſes perfected, Carts likewiſe are to be made, and ſhowed them, that looking on all theſe things, they may yield better faith to us: That beſides theſe, we can do many other Miracles which He himſelf in this World did; ſuch are healing the Sick, and raiſing the Dead; ſo that we obey but his holy
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:58998:76"/>Commands, have been Baptized with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Name of the only God, and by his inviſible Grace have been cleanſed from our ſins: That theſe Arms were given us by him to take Vengeance on thoſe who withſtand the Propagation of Truth. Theſe beginnings in Blandiſhing them ſhould have been uſed, and many of them whoſe Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ognomy declared them fitteſt, choſen our, and bred up in this Doctrine; and after ſent out like that <hi>Samaritan,</hi> to call in their People and fellow Citizens, with all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetude and Kindneſs, and without any Cruelty or Avarice, perſwading them that we care for Gold no more then they, and that we only uſe it for Exchange of things, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after it without any Covetouſneſs; and ſhewing them that inſtead of Gold we bring them Iron; much more uſeful then Gold, both for Tilling the Earth, and protecting the Life of Man. All which accompliſhed a great number of thoſe People ſhould be Shipt, as if by Divine command revealed to the <hi>Pope</hi> and King of <hi>Spain,</hi> into whoſe Regions they are to be brought and diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into the Colonys of <hi>Affrica,</hi> whence they are to be Tranſported into <hi>Spain</hi> to Labour,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:58998:76"/>Till the Earth, and Exerciſe <hi>Mechanick</hi> Arts, whilſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> addict themſelves to Arms, and by degrees ſubdue that whole Region. But the <hi>Spaniards</hi> that firſt entred there, were Rude and meer Souldiers igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant how much the Opinion of a Divinity prevails over the mind of man to ſubject him; but as ſoon as they entred the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of their neareſt Enemies, began to ſnatch at Gold openly, ſhewing that they had little care of their Salvation; and threatning them without any premiſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, that they ſhould ſuffer themſelves to be Baptized, and believe <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified for them. Which things at firſt ſight were abſurd, to wit, That Water ſhould bring any one to Heaven, or that a God could Die; and was ſtraightway at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry firſt a Stumbling-block to them, as the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, not obſerving the Apoſtolick Canon, <hi>Preach to men.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">13. Such a Method of Chriſtian Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, have the moſt diligent Propagators of the <hi>Ignatian</hi> Faith obſerved in our Times, in the utmoſt Provinces of <hi>Aſia;</hi> for they when they took notice that even thoſe, though very few, remains of the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi>
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:58998:77"/>Doctrine which yet kept Footing in <hi>Europe,</hi> contained ſomething harſh and hard, ſo that as of old they ſeemed to the <hi>Greeks</hi> fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to the <hi>Jews</hi> a ſtumbling-block; they forbore to Preach <hi>Chriſt</hi> Crucified, whom only <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſed to know, and ſet up another Chriſt, Beautiful, Splendid, Clad in <hi>Chineſs</hi> habit, who with wonderful Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence had formerly deſcended from Heaven into <hi>Europe,</hi> and foretold the Reign of our <hi>Pope.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Palafor. in Epiſt. ad Innoc. x. Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. viii. Joan. And alſo in Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio de Mr. de St. Amour. Doctoris Sorbon alegato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
                     <hi>Nothing Preached they of Chriſt Crucified, nothing of Mortification, nothing of Faſting, nothing of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, nothing of year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that if the Church would again teach the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and Inſtruct them in the right Rules of Faith, they would oppoſe it, and cry out they were deceived; for no Faſting Religion, no Penitent and Weeping Faith dreadful to Nature, enemy to the Fleſh, deſtined to Death and Danger; No Saviour Crucified had their Maſters the Jeſuits told them of: They will proteſt they Embraced him not as Man and God, Scourged, Spit on,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:58998:77"/>Contemned, loaden with Wounds, hanging on the Croſs, and Dead, but received a Saviour, Beautiful, Lovely, Glorious</hi> (ſuch as the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits paint him in the <hi>Chineſs</hi> habit) <hi>and a Law and courſe of Life, Eaſie, Pleaſant, Sweet, Delightful, Merry and Peaceable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">14. Yet this new Method ſome have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowed, and among thoſe great ſtirs were raiſed in this matter, by <hi>John Palafox de Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doza, Biſhop of the City of Angels in America, and Dean of the Counſel of the Indies,</hi> a man too Simple and Rude to underſtand theſe Arts. He poſſibly imagined with himſelf that <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema,</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> pronounced,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Even againſt an Angel from Heaven preaching any other Goſpel,</hi> was to this day, and even in the <hi>Indies</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of force; and did not rightly Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret another ſaying of the ſame St. <hi>Paul, So that Chriſt be Preached,</hi> that is ſo that <hi>Chriſts</hi> Name be retained. Led by which Errors, this Moroſe old man publickly damn'd that <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> Catechiſm, whereupon it was no wonder if he were diſturbed in his Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, caſt out of the City, and by the <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Society made a comman Laughing-ſtock, having a Croſs put upon him made of Bulls
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:58998:78"/>Horns, whilſt they ſung as a Litany, <hi>From Biſhop Palafox, Good Lord deliver us,</hi> as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Letters moſt lamentably com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains. Certainly he that thus durſt ſtickle for the ancient Purity and Simplicity of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was worthy to be turned out of doors; there eternally and bitterly to Weep, and exerciſe Faſting, as long as he pleaſed.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Indeed many good and ſimple Men throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> were much offended at the declarations; and importunate complaints of this Biſhop, and ſuch like imprudent Men: whom that the <hi>Pope</hi> might in ſome meaſure ſatisfie; and perhaps being juſtly fearful, by ſacred edict he reſtrained the publication of that Method; the inſtrument of which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition was lately tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted us by <hi>Hurtado</hi> a Spaniſh Divine.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Thomas Hurt. in Opuſc. Colon. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 1655.</note> But that Cenſure is not at all to be interpreted, as rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> Inhabiting beyond <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and the Equinoctial Line, when it was only made in favour of thoſe who yet in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> retain ſome remains of ancient Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; as to omit others the famous <hi>Didacus de Moralez,</hi> a Jeſuite, Rector of the Colledge
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:58998:78"/>of St. <hi>Joſeph,</hi> in the City of <hi>Manilia,</hi> which is the Capital of the <hi>Phillipines,</hi> has taught us in one entire and ſolid volume.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. And ſince things are ſo, I believe that the ſafeſt way which the Emperours of old, held in Converting the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth into a Dominion. For as they left ſome reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances of the late liberty, though the liberty was wholly taken away, ſo it will be convenient to expoſe ſome image of Chriſt; though himſelf by degrees be utterly aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. To which end, we may obſerve the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the moſt Religious <hi>Machiavel. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever would innovate the form of the Commonwealth in that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Diſput. de Repub. lib. 1. c. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>it is neceſſary that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſome ſhadow of things that were before; for ſo it comes to paſs, that the People do not think any thing changed, though all things be innovated: For the People uſe to look no farther then things are Viſible, and outward appearances; and as ſuch takes and receives them, though the Magiſtrate plainly creates new things, and new duties are impoſed upon Men; yet retaining the ſame names, they are thought ſtill to be the ſame.</hi> Hence may evidently be gathered.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:58998:79"/>
            <head>The <hi>CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Since the Condition and State of things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits not, that Chriſt be taken from the midſt of us by open Violence, 'tis adviſeable to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch Him by a lingering Conſumption; and whilſt He Withers and Pines away by <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh</hi> or <hi>Egyptian</hi> Arts, ſo temper, harden and paint Him over, that He may be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon duller Underſtandings, as the Image of a lively and perfect body. Which Arts, that I may truly ſet forth, and particularly explain, I humbly ſupplicate that Spirit which reſides in the Cabinet of our <hi>Popes</hi> Breſt, not to think we unworthy of his Guidance and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration: And you likewiſe <hi>Moſt Reverend Men,</hi> aſſiſt me with your Prayers and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to him.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dated in the Library of the great <hi>Convent,</hi> 
                  <date>theſe <hi>Calends</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> MDcLxvii.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58998:79"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
